<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>TCET Open Source Blog</title>
        <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog</link>
        <description>TCET Open Source Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CNCF Zero to Merge - Your first step towards Open-Source]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/2023/10/10/CNCF-Zero-to-Merge-Your-first-step-towards-Open-Source</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/2023/10/10/CNCF-Zero-to-Merge-Your-first-step-towards-Open-Source</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[CNCF LOGO]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="CNCF LOGO" src="/assets/images/CNCF_Logo-25a8519af09f7f29fe508e734646f913.jpg" width="1663" height="871" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2><p>This blog summarizes my experience with the Cloud Native Computing Foundation's first edition of the newly launched Zero to Merge Incubator Program. This program was launched with the primary aim of getting new folks involved in Open-Source. I learned about this program from one of the LinkedIn posts by <a href="https://github.com/rohitg00" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rohit Ghumare</a>. If you are willing to register for the program, you can check out the link <a href="https://project.linuxfoundation.org/cncf-zero-to-merge-application" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>. CNCF will not conduct any such programs as of this year, but you should keep an eye on the page for future proposals.</p><p>The CNCF Zero to Merge Program is a 4-week long program with 2 sessions per week. According to the Indian Standard Time, the sessions were held on Monday and Thursday from 9:30 p.m. to 10:30 p.m. each week.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="during-the-program">During the program<a href="#during-the-program" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to During the program" title="Direct link to During the program">​</a></h2><p><strong>Week 1 Session 1</strong>: The initial session of the program's first week served as an orientation, acquainting participants with the program itself, its instructor, and the schedule. This session predominantly centered on key topics, including an introduction to open-source principles and the CNCF (Cloud Native Computing Foundation). It also covered the art of selecting suitable open-source projects for contribution and the necessary prerequisites for effective participation in the open-source community.</p><p><strong>Week 1 Session 2:</strong> During the second session of the first week, participants focused on acquiring knowledge about essential tools like CLOTributor for narrowing down project options that align with individual preferences. The session also delved into important concepts such as GitHub and Git basics, GitHub Actions, and expanded insights into The Linux Foundation.</p><p><strong>Week 2 Session 1:</strong> In the second week of our CNCF program, we delved into the history and progress of CNCF projects, exploring what motivates individuals to contribute to open-source initiatives. Our instructor, Taylor Dolezal, left a lasting impression with his fantastic and approachable teaching style. In addition to valuable insights, he provided a practical demonstration of the entire process, from forking a repository to creating a pull request (PR).</p><p><strong>Week 2 Session 2:</strong> The session was centered around exploring the topics of Cloud Native Evolution and Cloud Native Trends, featuring active engagement through a question-and-answer format where the instructor either provided answers or directed participants to relevant articles and white papers. Towards the end, attendees were tasked with homework, which involved finding a project that aligned with their interests in the subject matter.</p><p><strong>Week 3 Session 1:</strong> In the third week, participants were allowed to take the spotlight by presenting their screens. They were encouraged to share their involvement in various projects, showcasing their approach to addressing the issues at hand and detailing their interactions with project maintainers.</p><p><strong>Week 3 Session 2</strong>: This session was primarily intended for clearing doubts and addressing any questions or uncertainties participants may have had.</p><p><strong>Week 4 Session 1:</strong> The first session of the last week had the following agenda: Hot seat opportunity: During this segment, participants had the chance to share information about their projects, issues, or the specific focus of their pull requests, offering an opportunity for discussion and feedback. Live lesson: The session included a live lesson where the participants reviewed the CNCF (Cloud Native Computing Foundation) website and learned how to navigate through its resources and additional learning materials.</p><p><strong>Week 4 Session 2:</strong> The program has concluded, marking a moment of celebration, friendly conversations, and discussions about the future steps for all the attendees.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="key-takeaways-from-the-program">Key Takeaways from the Program<a href="#key-takeaways-from-the-program" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways from the Program" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways from the Program">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="CNCF" src="/assets/images/cncf2-a16b7cf0d5b87711fcc6b75ff00b8ebe.png" width="1178" height="443" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>CNCF Zero to Merge is a great program for beginners to open source. It provides guidance and mentorship to help you contribute to open source for the first time.</p><p>Here's a summary of the process:</p><p><strong>1. Find a Project:</strong> Choose a CNCF incubating project that interests you and has welcoming maintainers.</p><p><strong>2. Understand the Issue:</strong> Read the issue or bug report you want to work on thoroughly and clarify any doubts with the maintainers.</p><p><strong>3. Fork the Repository:</strong> Create a fork of the project's repository on your GitHub account to work on your changes separately.</p><p><strong>4. Make a Branch:</strong> Create a new branch in your fork to isolate your work and make it easier to create a pull request later.</p><p><strong>5. Make the Changes:</strong> Code the fix or feature as described in the issue. You can do this locally and then push the changes to your forked repository.</p><p><strong>6. Test Your Changes:</strong> Run any tests and commands mentioned in the project to ensure your changes work as intended. You may need to write new tests.</p><p><strong>7. Create a Pull Request:</strong> Using GitHub, create a pull request from your branch to the upstream repository. The maintainers will review your code and provide feedback.</p><p><strong>8. Iterate Based on Feedback:</strong> Make any requested changes based on the review and commit these changes to your branch so that the pull request updates automatically.</p><p><strong>9. Merge:</strong> Once the maintainers approve your changes, they will merge your pull request, and your contribution becomes part of the project.</p><p><strong>10. Celebrate:</strong> Congratulations, you've successfully made your first open-source contribution! You are now an official contributor to the project.</p><p>This program is a great way to get started with open source and can be very rewarding. It's important to be patient and open to feedback from maintainers, as it helps improve your skills and contribute positively to the project.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>This is a great step-by-step guide for making your first open-source contribution to a CNCF incubating project. It's important to follow these steps carefully to ensure a smooth and successful contribution experience.</p><p>The CNCF Zero to Merge initiative is a great way for newcomers to open source to get involved and make meaningful contributions. By focusing on small, self-contained issues that need fixing, new contributors can learn about the process of contributing to open-source projects and gain confidence. With proper mentorship and guidance, new contributors can progress from fixing typos to making more substantial code contributions that improve the project.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Web Crawling, A Beginner’s Perspective on Data Extraction]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/web-crawling</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/web-crawling</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this blog, you will explore the fundamentals of web crawling and how you can get started with your own data extraction projects.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>Web crawling, also known as web scraping, is the process of automatically extracting data from websites.
It allows us to gather valuable information from various sources on the internet efficiently and in a structured manner.
In this blog, we’ll explore the fundamentals of web crawling and how you can get started with your own data extraction projects.</em></p></blockquote><br><figure><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/web_crawl-fe3fa3d0b2b94658d3833b93c0a04f25.png" style="border:2px solid grey" class="img_ev3q"></figure><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-if-i-told-you-that-web-crawling-could-come-to-your-rescue-even-in-unexpected-work-scenarios-">What if I told you that web crawling could come to your rescue even in unexpected work scenarios? 🤔<a href="#what-if-i-told-you-that-web-crawling-could-come-to-your-rescue-even-in-unexpected-work-scenarios-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What if I told you that web crawling could come to your rescue even in unexpected work scenarios? 🤔" title="Direct link to What if I told you that web crawling could come to your rescue even in unexpected work scenarios? 🤔">​</a></h2><p>Imagine you’re on a relaxing weekend, enjoying your favorite Netflix series, when suddenly your boss calls with an urgent task.</p><p>Let’s say your boss needs a comprehensive analysis of competitors’ pricing for an upcoming project. Manually collecting this data from various websites would be time-consuming and error-prone.
However, with web crawling, you can <strong>automate the data extraction process</strong>, quickly gathering pricing information from multiple sources and generating a detailed report.
Not only does this save you hours of manual work, but it also <strong>ensures accuracy</strong> and <strong>provides valuable insights</strong> for your boss.</p><p>Web crawling can be a game-changer in various work scenarios. Need to gather customer reviews for a product launch?
Web crawling can swiftly scrape reviews from e-commerce platforms, allowing you to analyze sentiment and make data-driven decisions.
Want to monitor industry trends or track news updates? Web crawling can continuously fetch relevant information from news websites, keeping you up to date and enabling you to stay ahead of the competition.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="benefits">Benefits<a href="#benefits" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Benefits" title="Direct link to Benefits">​</a></h2><p>Let's have a look at the various benefits of web crawling that have made it a popular concept for seamless integration within large-scale enterprises.</p><figure><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/benefits-c183a0b67119a93e2de7cfbac13331cb.png" style="border:2px solid black" class="img_ev3q"><center><figcaption>Benefits of Web Crawling</figcaption></center></figure><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="process-of-web-crawling">Process of Web Crawling<a href="#process-of-web-crawling" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Process of Web Crawling" title="Direct link to Process of Web Crawling">​</a></h2><figure><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/process-38e97ec8a536b5182307fcd51963e2a7.png" style="border:2px solid black" class="img_ev3q"><center><figcaption>Process of Web Crawling</figcaption></center></figure><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>💡 Discovery</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>In the discovery stage, a web crawler starts by identifying set of seed URLs. These seed URLs are the starting points from which the crawler begins exploring the web. They can be manually provided or generated programmatically. The crawler then extracts the links present on the web page of the seed URLs and adds them to a queue for further processing.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>🕷️ Crawling</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>The crawling stage involves visiting the URLs in the queue and retrieving the corresponding web pages. The crawler sends HTTP requests to the web servers hosting the pages and receives HTTP responses in return. The responses typically include HTML content, but they can also include other types of files such as images, CSS files, or JavaScript files. The crawler parses the HTML content to extract links and other relevant information for subsequent crawling.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>⛏️ Fetching</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>During the fetching stage, the crawler retrieves the content of the web pages by downloading them from the web servers. This process involves downloading the HTML and any associated files, such as images or scripts, required to render the page correctly. The fetched content is then stored for further processing.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>💻 Rendering</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>Rendering refers to the process of processing and executing JavaScript code present on web pages. Some web pages heavily rely on JavaScript to load and display content dynamically. Modern web crawlers often include a rendering engine that can execute JavaScript code, allowing the crawler to handle pages that rely on client-side rendering.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>📑 Indexing</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>Once the web pages are fetched and rendered, the crawler can extract the desired data from the pages. This data can include text content, metadata, links, or any other relevant information. The extracted data is typically processed and stored in an organized manner, such as in a database or an index, for further analysis or retrieval.</div></div></div></details><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info alert alert--info admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>It’s important to note that web crawling is an iterative process.
As the crawler discovers new links during the crawling stage, it adds them to the queue for subsequent crawling, continuing the process of discovery, crawling, fetching, rendering, and indexing for a broader coverage of the web.</p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="getting-started-with-web-crawling">Getting Started with Web Crawling<a href="#getting-started-with-web-crawling" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting Started with Web Crawling" title="Direct link to Getting Started with Web Crawling">​</a></h2><ul><li><p><strong>Identify Your Data Needs</strong>: Determine the specific information you want to extract from websites.
It could be product details, contact information, news articles, or any other relevant data.</p></li><li><p><strong>Choose a Web Crawling Tool</strong>: There are various web crawling frameworks and libraries available, such as BeautifulSoup and Scrapy in Python.
Select a tool that aligns with your programming language and project requirements.</p></li></ul><blockquote><p><em>You can learn more about Python Scrapy <a href="https://docs.scrapy.org/en/latest/intro/tutorial.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>here</strong></a></em></p></blockquote><ul><li><p><strong>Understand the Website Structure</strong>: Familiarize yourself with the target website’s structure. Identify the HTML elements that contain the data you need, such as class names, IDs, or specific tags.
Some key steps to follow here may include:</p><div class="codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-text codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">1. Inspect the web page</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">2. Explore the HTML Elements</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">3. Identify unique Identifiers</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div></li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">Example: </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">product-name</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><ul><li><p><strong>Write the Crawling Code</strong>: Utilize your chosen web crawling tool to write code that navigates through the website, locates the desired data, and extracts it.
This involves sending HTTP requests, parsing HTML content, and selecting the relevant elements.</p></li><li><p><strong>Handle Website-Specific Challenges</strong>: Some websites may implement anti-crawling measures like CAPTCHA or rate limiting.
Implement strategies like rotating IP addresses or adding delays in your crawling code to handle such challenges.</p></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ethical-considerations">Ethical Considerations<a href="#ethical-considerations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ethical Considerations" title="Direct link to Ethical Considerations">​</a></h2><p>While web crawling can be a powerful tool for data extraction, it’s important to respect website owners’ terms of service and adhere to ethical guidelines. Always ensure that your crawling activities are legal and ethical.
Be mindful of any website-specific crawling policies and consider reaching out to website owners for permission when necessary.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>Web crawling opens up a world of possibilities for data extraction and analysis. By automating the process of gathering data from websites, you can save time and collect valuable insights. Armed with the knowledge from this beginner’s guide, you’re ready to embark on your web crawling journey.
Remember to stay ethical, explore different tools, and continue learning as you dive deeper into the exciting world of web crawling.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>web crawling</category>
            <category>data extraction</category>
            <category>automation</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Blockchain - Future of Tommorow]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-blockchain</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-blockchain</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Blockchain - Future of Tommorow]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Ever wondered what blockchain is and how it looks? Let's explore the realm of blockchain together. This blog focuses on the basics of blockchain technology along with its applications. In this evolving era, it is important to understand this technology because, according to  recent research, blockchain has the potential to reshape the future and the way we perceive it.</p></blockquote><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Blockchain" src="/assets/images/BlockChain-70c48f97585422cd78e1dc331866cab3.jpg" width="964" height="723" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Blockchain technology</em></td></tr></tbody></table><br><h1><em>What is Blockchain</em> ?</h1><br><p>Distributed database and immutable ledger used for recording transactions, tracking assets  and building trust is termed as blockchain.<br>
Let’s take an example:<br>
Imagine a blockchain as a super secure digital notebook for businesses. This notebook stores information in a special way. Instead of writing everything in one long list, it divides the information into blocks and connects them like a chain.
What's cool about this digital notebook is that once something is written in it, you can't erase it or change it without everyone in the network agreeing. It's like having a magical pen that only writes the truth.
So, businesses use blockchain to keep an unchangeable record of things like orders, payments, and accounts. It's like a super reliable ledger that makes sure nobody sneaks in fake or unauthorized entries. Everybody in the network sees the same information, so there's no confusion.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-blocks-of-blockchain-consist-of-"><em>What does blocks of Blockchain consist of</em> ?<a href="#what-does-blocks-of-blockchain-consist-of-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-blocks-of-blockchain-consist-of-" title="Direct link to what-does-blocks-of-blockchain-consist-of-">​</a></h2><br><p>Blocks are the place or container which stores all information of user like transaction data being one of many examples and once the data is stored in blocks it cannot be altered again.</p><ul><li>Data : It is gives information about the user.</li><li><a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/blockchain-hash-function/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Hash</strong></a>: A hash is a mathematical function that turns any kind of information into a secret code with a specific length. It's like a machine that takes in any size of data and spits out a code that's always the same size</li><li>Hash of previous block : Every consequent blocks are connected with the hash of previous block. So if any one alters the one block the whole chain will get disrupted and with this it is easy to track where the data alteration is performed.<br><br></li></ul><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Blocks of Blockchain" src="/assets/images/Blocks-of-blockchain-b87380545f32ba7af223ba5f0c0b80cb.png" width="886" height="454" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Blocks of Blockchain</em></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="different-types-of-blockchain-technology"><em>Different types of Blockchain Technology</em><a href="#different-types-of-blockchain-technology" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to different-types-of-blockchain-technology" title="Direct link to different-types-of-blockchain-technology">​</a></h2><br><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>Public Blockchain </b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>Here anyone and everyone can participate in the core activities of the blockchain network. In this network system problems like centralization, less security, and less transparency don’t exist as it uses Distributed Ledger Technology( which means data is distributed across the network) . The very first example of this is Bitcoin. It enables everyone to perform transactions. Other examples of this include Litcoin and Ethereum. Use cases of public networks are in Document Validation and cryptocurrency.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>Private Blockchain </b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>A private blockchain is like a special club for a group of people or organizations. In this club, only those who are invited can join and participate. It's not open to the public, like the internet. Just like a public network it also stores data in a decentralised manner. As they are limited in their size, the transaction takes place very fast. "You can think of private blockchains as being the intranet, while the public blockchains are more like the internet," Godefroy said. Use cases of this are supply chain, internal voting, and asset ownership.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>Hybrid Blockchain </b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>In simpler words, a hybrid network is a combination of both private and public networks. Companies like real estate which want to keep some of their data private and need to show some information to the public like listings, use this type of network. According to Godfroy medical records can also be stored on this blockchain network where users can access their data without any third-party interruption.</div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>Consortium Blockchain </b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div>A consortium blockchain, also called a federated blockchain, combines features of both private and public blockchains. It's like a mix of the two. In this type of blockchain, several organizations work together on a shared network, and not just one entity has control, reducing the risks. It is more like a team effort instead of just one person or organization being in charge. Use cases for this network are Banking and payment.</div></div></div></details><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-blockchain-is-becoming-integral-part-of-our-life-"><em>Why Blockchain is becoming integral part of our life</em> ?<a href="#why-blockchain-is-becoming-integral-part-of-our-life-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to why-blockchain-is-becoming-integral-part-of-our-life-" title="Direct link to why-blockchain-is-becoming-integral-part-of-our-life-">​</a></h2><br><p>Blockchain technology has become a buzzword in recent times. Companies, institutions, and various transactions are rapidly adopting blockchain technology. Its popularity extends beyond cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin, and following are the important reasons why blockchain is gaining prominence:<br><br></p><p> 1) <b>Decentalization</b><br>
Traditionally, we relied on centralized authorities like banks and governments for our transactions and record-keeping. Additionally, the risks of data tampering and alteration were more significant than one could imagine. To address these issues, blockchain has emerged as a solution. At its core, blockchain embodies the concept of decentralization, which means data is not stored in one central location or controlled by a single organization. Instead, it enables the distribution of control and verification across a network of participants.</p><p>2) <b>Smart Contracts</b><br>
<a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/smart-contracts#:~:text=Next%20Steps-,Smart%20contracts%20defined,intermediary's%20involvement%20or%20time%20loss." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Smart Contracts</strong></a>, residing on blockchain technology, execute automatically when predefined conditions are satisfied, eliminating the need for intermediaries such as banks or attorneys. Parties encode contract terms, ensuring immediate execution upon meeting conditions, reducing costs, and optimizing efficiency.</p><p>3) <b> Transparency and Security</b><br>
Blockchain technology provides a transparent system where all activities are visible to the public. Since blockchain is a decentralized and distributed ledger, all transactions on the internet are accessible to all network participants. Blockchain achieves transparency through the use of encryption methods for secure and unchangeable record-keeping. Blockchain security results from a combination of distributed consensus and cryptographic techniques.</p><p>4) <b>Intellectual Property (IP)</b><br>
Intellectual property (IP) in blockchain involves ownership of digital assets, patents for blockchain innovations, smart contracts for IP agreements, and open-source licensing. Few methods with which blockchain technology make use of IP is: Patent, Copyrights,Trademarks and Trade secrets.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="applications-of-blockchain"><em>Applications of Blockchain</em><a href="#applications-of-blockchain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to applications-of-blockchain" title="Direct link to applications-of-blockchain">​</a></h2><br><p>Today, we cannot imagine our lives without the internet. It has become an integral part of our daily routines. Almost everything we do happens through the internet, and in some ways, we are highly dependent on it. Due to the sudden rise in the popularity of blockchain in the previous decade, it is estimated that, like the internet, blockchain will also become an integral part of our lives. It's applicatiion ranges from transaction, healthcare, cryptocurrency, <a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/what-is-bitcoin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>bitcoin</strong></a>, IoT and what not. The part of the tech industry that deals with online data and services is about to go through a big and important change because of blockchain technology.</p><br><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Applications of Blockchain" src="/assets/images/Blockchain-Applications-6cd85bace6e8b17301af3c908a95a546.webp" width="600" height="548" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Applications of Blockchain</em></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="let-us-have-a-look-at-some-drawbacks-of-blockchain-technology"><em>Let us have a look at some drawbacks of Blockchain technology</em><a href="#let-us-have-a-look-at-some-drawbacks-of-blockchain-technology" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to let-us-have-a-look-at-some-drawbacks-of-blockchain-technology" title="Direct link to let-us-have-a-look-at-some-drawbacks-of-blockchain-technology">​</a></h2><br><ul><li>The implementation cost of blockchain is very high. For a small company, it becomes difficult to shift to blockchain technology because they need to hire a skilled blockchain developer, and in addition to this, infrastructure costs will also be incurred, which require a significant amount of funding.</li><li>The continuous operation of mining, minting, and transaction validation demands powerful systems that run non-stop. Beyond substantial investments, these activities consume significant amounts of energy, resulting in potentially severe environmental repercussions.
To address the negative environmental impact, China has taken the step of banning blockchain mining in the Inner Mongolia region.</li><li>In the context of blockchain networks like Bitcoin, a 51% attack occurs when a single entity or group of entities controls more than 50% of the network's mining or computational power. This level of control can potentially allow them to manipulate transactions and disrupt the normal functioning of the network.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion"><em>Conclusion</em><a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to conclusion" title="Direct link to conclusion">​</a></h2><br><p>In conclusion, blockchain's decentralization, smart contracts, and transparency offer transformative solutions across industries. Despite high implementation costs and environmental concerns, its impact is undeniable. Just as the internet integrated into daily life, blockchain is poised to shape the future of transactions and data management, promising an exciting path in technology and business.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Blockchain</category>
            <category>Data</category>
            <category>Software</category>
            <category>Technology</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Basics of GNU/Linux]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/linux-basics</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/linux-basics</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this blog, you will understand the basic concept of the linux kernel and it's ecosystem in system softwares.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Linux is an operating system kernel. It was originally written in 1991 by Linus Torvalds for his personal use, and it was soon adopted as the kernel for the GNU operating system, which was written to be a free (libre) replacement for Unix. </p><p>So, what even is GNU/Linux? What is free software? You must have so many more questions! Through this blog, we will try to understand what is linux, and why it is the most popular operating system in the world. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-world-of-operating-systems">The world of operating systems<a href="#the-world-of-operating-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The world of operating systems" title="Direct link to The world of operating systems">​</a></h2><p>Most modern opearting systems can be grouped into two categories:</p><ul><li>Microsoft NT descendants like Windows XP to Windows 11, Xbox OS, Windows Phone</li><li>Unix based (Mostly everything apart from Windows)</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-unix-based">Why UNIX based?<a href="#why-unix-based" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why UNIX based?" title="Direct link to Why UNIX based?">​</a></h3><p>Well, the answer is simple. Most of unix-based operating systems are free to use or modify, and hence are widely adopted. UNIX itself has died today, however, it's clones and descendants are still alive. Some of these operating systems are direct clones of the UNIX source code, while some such as Linux are UNIX-like. Errr.. so unix-based, unix-like, what are all these?</p><p>Don't worry, I will cover this in the next section. What's important in this section is you understand the fact almost everything that is not based on Microsoft NT is a direct or indirect descendant of UNIX. Some examples of operating systems that are descendants of UNIX are:</p><ol><li>Linux and it's derivative distributions</li><li>Mac OS X</li><li>BSD </li><li>ChromeOS </li><li>Android</li><li>PS4 OS</li></ol><p>Why is this important? Because all of these operating systems here share a plethora of common core functionailty. To put it simply, most of their internals and most of their functions are same, if not, similar. For example, all of these operating systems have the same basic commands.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="history-of-operating-systems">History of operating systems<a href="#history-of-operating-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to History of operating systems" title="Direct link to History of operating systems">​</a></h2><p>Since most of the operating systems today can trace their lineage to UNIX, it is important to atleast have a brief idea of what UNIX is, even though the original versions of UNIX no longer survive. Understanding the history will also help you understand why UNIX-based commands do not work on something like Windows.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-unix">What is UNIX?<a href="#what-is-unix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is UNIX?" title="Direct link to What is UNIX?">​</a></h3><p>UNIX was an operating system, developed at Bell labs in mid 1960s. Many of their innovations and design choices of the original UNIX team have lived up to 60+ years, well into the 2020s. These design choices include the idea of a multiuser operating system and a hierarchical filesystem.</p><p>UNIX truely is the grandfather of all modern operating systems. All of these features that were built into different versions of the original UNIX operating system still exist in operating systems like Mac OS, Android, linux distributions and basically every thing that can trace their lineage back to UNIX.</p><p>Since Microsoft operating systems cannot trace back their lineage to UNIX, all UNIX features do not work on windows. The commands that you can run colloquially on both MacOS and Linux, do not exist natively on Windows. Windows has it's own commands, and it's own way of doing things.</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/history-a65f57edaf967fad570d7218cbab6b4f.png" width="900" height="722" class="img_ev3q"></p><p align="center"><b>FIG 1:</b> UNIX's descendants</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="closed-source-mixed-source-and-open-source">Closed Source, Mixed Source, and Open Source<a href="#closed-source-mixed-source-and-open-source" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closed Source, Mixed Source, and Open Source" title="Direct link to Closed Source, Mixed Source, and Open Source">​</a></h3><p>In the diagram in the above section, you can see a legend in the top right that annotates the color codes given in the diagram. These are:</p><ul><li><b>Closed Source</b> (denoted by Red): These were descendants of UNIX that were further developed by companies like Sun Microsystem, HP, etc. The source code of these developements of UNIX were strictly guarded. The code itself was kept a secret from the public and the clients did not have the permission to change or alter the source code in anyway. Each company had their own non-permissive license.</li><li><b>Mixed Source</b> (denoted by Yellow): These were the descendants of UNIX that were further developed by colleges like Univesity of California, Berkeley, and many others. Berkeley was influential as they had released a mixed source code license (also known as BSD license), that would allow sharing and modification of the source code, with other colleges and companies, for educational or other purposes.</li><li><b>Open Source</b> (denoted by Green): These were descendants of UNIX whose developement was done in public as their source code was made freely available for everyone to view, modify, and use. The license that governed open source software were early versions of the GNU public license(GPL). The GPL from the early days has been a really permissive license as it allowed inspection and modification of the source code as per requirement.</li></ul><p>Licensing was the key differentiator in all of these descendants of UNIX, as they governed what could be done with the operating system. Companies have to make a profit, and colleges have to follow certain rules, hence we can understand why the first two cases wanted to safeguard their code behind non-permissive licenses. But why did the third case not want to protect their code?</p><p>The answer is, as mentioned in the above two scenarios, software was a commodity that had to be purchased. The closed source versions were to be bought by clients. (Just like you buy a windows license). These were expensive to do so and also there were limited innovations in the software, like only in the company who built it or the college where it was developed. Hence, the Free Software Foundation was formed in the late 80s to solve this issue, and that is why they had created the GPL.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="free-software-foundation-fsf">Free Software Foundation (FSF)<a href="#free-software-foundation-fsf" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Free Software Foundation (FSF)" title="Direct link to Free Software Foundation (FSF)">​</a></h3><p>The free software foundation was built as a part of the free software movement in response to proprietary and restricted software. Free is not equal to free in terms of money. Free as FREEDOM. That was FSF's motto.</p><p>The movement's philosophy is that computers and software should not prevent cooperation between users, and instead should have the goal of liberating everyone in the cyberspace. This will encourage innovation in software. </p><p>According to the movement's leader <b>Richard Stallman</b>:</p><blockquote><p>Users should have the freedom to run, copy, distribute, study, change, and improve software.</p></blockquote><p>This was a visionary statement as open source software allowed ground-breaking innovations in the software industry and today, most of the software we use, have some kind of free software in them, either completly or in parts.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-gnulinux">What is GNU/Linux?<a href="#what-is-gnulinux" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is GNU/Linux?" title="Direct link to What is GNU/Linux?">​</a></h3><p>Richard Stallman was the leader of a group of developers who wanted to create an open source version of the UNIX operating systems. Remember, most of the UNIX descendants like System V or BSD were closed source or mixed source? The open source operating system needed to have everything that normally came with UNIX. The components had to be FREE, as stated in the previous section.</p><p>In 1984, they began working on the GNU project (GNU stands for GNU's not UNIX). Creating an operating systems however is a daunting task, even for the most experienced developers. Luckily for him, at the same time, a student in the University of Helsinki, Linus Torvalds was working on his operating system kernel, called Linux. </p><p>In any operating system, the <b>kernel</b> is the most important and critical component. The kernel facilitates the interaction of the the hardware and other system software. At that time, while most parts of the GNU project were complete (including gcc -  compiler, open source implementations of all unix-commands, etc), the project lacked a kernel. Linus Torvalds combined his Linux kernel with the rest of the components of the GNU ecosystem, to create a full operating system. This was known as <b>GNU/Linux</b>.</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/kernel-16775a222a3cff4a30c60b705413958f.png" width="800" height="632" class="img_ev3q"></p><p align="center"><b>FIG 2:</b> Kernel in operating system</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="linux-is-an-operating-system-kernel-that-along-with-other-system-software-components-creates-an-complete-operating-system-called-as-linux-distribution">Linux is an operating system kernel that along with other system software components creates an complete operating system called as linux distribution.<a href="#linux-is-an-operating-system-kernel-that-along-with-other-system-software-components-creates-an-complete-operating-system-called-as-linux-distribution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Linux is an operating system kernel that along with other system software components creates an complete operating system called as linux distribution." title="Direct link to Linux is an operating system kernel that along with other system software components creates an complete operating system called as linux distribution.">​</a></h4><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="difference-between-unix-based-vs-unix-like">Difference between unix-based vs unix-like<a href="#difference-between-unix-based-vs-unix-like" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Difference between unix-based vs unix-like" title="Direct link to Difference between unix-based vs unix-like">​</a></h3><p>In FIG 1, you can see that many of the closed and mixed source operating systems are directly linked to the original UNIX. This is because the companies and colleges that wanted to develop their own versions of UNIX paid a royalty to Bell Labs to acquire UNIX. This might sound contradictary to their own non-permissive licenses. However Bell labs decided that they did not want to be in the operating systems buisness, and instead wanted to focus on telecommunication and phone buisness. Hence they happily sold off their versions of UNIX. Since these companies directly got their versions of UNIX from Bell labs, their descendant operating systems were called <b>unix-like</b>. </p><p>There are a bit of legal reasons too that I will not cover in the blog as it is out of scope for our discussion, but to put it in simple terms, there was a foundation formed by a few of these companies called <b>The Open Group</b>, and they defined the UNIX standard according to their developements of UNIX. In FIG 1, you can see that most of the operating systems do not have a direct connection to UNIX. This is because even though they are based on the original UNIX and are compatible with the UNIX standards, they have not been certified by The Open Group. This is often due to financial considerations, as open source projects do not have a definite source of income. Hence these operating systems are called <b>Unix-like</b>. It is basically a matter of certification by The Open Group, simply put.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="linux-distributions">Linux Distributions<a href="#linux-distributions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Linux Distributions" title="Direct link to Linux Distributions">​</a></h2><p>You know that Linux is actually an operating system kernel and not an entire operating system in itself. When people talk about a linux based operating system, they are actually referring to Linux Distributions (often shorten to linux distro). Normally, a Linux Distribution bundles the linux kernel, a bunch of GNU tools, a shell, a package manager, a windowing system, and a window manager or desktop enviroment at the very least. On top of that, a linux distribution often can include utility software such as web browsers, a file explorer, a text editor, etc.
Did you know that Linux is actually an operating system kernel and not an entire operating system in itself? When people talk about a linux based operating system, they are actually referring to Linux Distributions. Normally, a Linux Distribution bundles the linux kernel, a bunch of GNU tools, a shell, a package manager, a windowing system, and a window manager or desktop enviroment at the very least. On top of that, a linux distribution often can include utility software such as web browsers, a file explorer, a text editor, etc.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="types-of-linux-distributions">Types of Linux Distributions<a href="#types-of-linux-distributions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of Linux Distributions" title="Direct link to Types of Linux Distributions">​</a></h3><p>While there are hundreds of linux distributions, most of them are based on a few original ones. These are:</p><ul><li>Arch Linux</li><li>Debian Linux</li><li>Red Hat Linux</li><li>Slackware</li><li>Gentoo</li><li>NixOS</li><li>Void Linux</li></ul><p>The key difference between these distributions are usually their package managers. However, different distributions may choose to ship different types of components. Let's look at them in brief:</p><table><thead><tr><th>Distribution</th><th>Package Manager</th><th>init system</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Arch Linux</td><td>pacman</td><td>systemd</td></tr><tr><td>Debian</td><td>apt or dpkg</td><td>systemd</td></tr><tr><td>Red Hat</td><td>dnf or yum</td><td>systemd</td></tr><tr><td>Slackware</td><td>slackpkg</td><td>bsd-style</td></tr><tr><td>Gentoo</td><td>portage</td><td>openrc</td></tr><tr><td>NixOS</td><td>nix</td><td>systemd</td></tr><tr><td>Void Linux</td><td>xbps</td><td>runit</td></tr></tbody></table><p>These distributions are often called parent distributions as many other distributions are derived from them. Derivatives retain the package manager of the parent distributions while shipping different components. For example - a different shell, a different filesystem, etc.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="well-known-derivative-distributions">Well known derivative distributions<a href="#well-known-derivative-distributions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Well known derivative distributions" title="Direct link to Well known derivative distributions">​</a></h4><ul><li><b>Arch based</b>: Manjaro, EndeavourOS, Garuda Linux</li><li><b>Debian based</b>: Ubuntu, Linux Mint, ElementaryOS</li><li><b>Red Hat Based</b>: Fedora, CentOS, RockyLinux</li><li><b>Gentoo based:</b> RedstarOS, Funtoo</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="core-components-of-a-distribution">Core Components of a distribution<a href="#core-components-of-a-distribution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Core Components of a distribution" title="Direct link to Core Components of a distribution">​</a></h3><p>As we have discussed, a linux distro comes with the linux kernel, a shell, a filesystem, a bunch of GNU tools, and other system software. Let us discuss in brief what each of these components do, and how they help the operating system function.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="kernel">Kernel<a href="#kernel" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Kernel" title="Direct link to Kernel">​</a></h4><p>The kernel is a computer program at the core of a computer's operating system and generally has complete control over everything in the system. It is the portion of the operating system code that is always resident in memory and facilitates interactions between hardware and software components.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="init-system">Init System<a href="#init-system" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Init System" title="Direct link to Init System">​</a></h4><p>Init system (short of for <i>initialization</i>), is the first process started during booting of the operating system. Init is a daemon process that continues running until the system is shut down. It is the direct or indirect ancestor of all other processes and automatically adopts all orphaned processes. Init is started by the kernel during the booting process. The process ID of init system is <b>PID 1</b>. </p><p>The init system with the help of the kernel initialises all hardware on the computer. The init scripts are launched by the init process to guarantee basic functionality on system start and shutdown. This includes (un)mounting of file systems and launching of daemons (background services).</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="filesystem">Filesystem<a href="#filesystem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Filesystem" title="Direct link to Filesystem">​</a></h4><p>A file system or filesystem controls how data is stored and retrieved. Without a file system, information placed in a storage medium would be one large body of data with no way to tell where one piece of information stops and the next begins. By separating the data into pieces and giving each piece a name, the information is easily isolated and identified. Taking its name from the way paper-based information systems are named, each group of data is called a "file". The structure and logic rules used to manage the groups of information and their names is called a "file system".</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-shell">The shell<a href="#the-shell" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The shell" title="Direct link to The shell">​</a></h4><p>From Wikipedia: </p><blockquote><p>A Unix shell is a command-line interpreter or shell that provides a traditional user interface for the Unix operating system and for Unix-like systems. Users direct the operation of the computer by entering commands as text for a command line interpreter to execute or by creating text scripts of one or more such commands.</p></blockquote><p>A shell is a computer interface to an operating system. It exposes the operating systems' services (init system for example) to human users. The shell takes our commands, and gives them to the operating system to perform. It is called a shell because it is an outer protective layer around the operating system.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="gnu-tools">GNU tools<a href="#gnu-tools" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to GNU tools" title="Direct link to GNU tools">​</a></h4><p>These are important tools that are present in some or other form since the UNIX days. The GNU toolchain is a broad collection of programming tools produced by the GNU Project. These tools form a toolchain (a suite of tools used in a serial manner) used for developing software applications and operating systems. </p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="package-manager">Package manager<a href="#package-manager" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Package manager" title="Direct link to Package manager">​</a></h4><p>From Wikipedia:</p><blockquote><p>A package manager or package-management system is a collection of software tools that automates the process of installing, upgrading, configuring, and removing computer programs for a computer in a consistent manner.</p></blockquote><p>A package manager deals with packages, distributions of software and data in archive files. Packages contain metadata, such as the software's name, description of its purpose, version number, vendor, checksum (preferably a cryptographic hash function), and a list of dependencies necessary for the software to run properly. Upon installation, metadata is stored in a local package database. Package managers typically maintain a database of software dependencies and version information to prevent software mismatches and missing prerequisites. They work closely with software repositories, binary repository managers, and app stores. </p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="desktop-enviroment">Desktop Enviroment<a href="#desktop-enviroment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Desktop Enviroment" title="Direct link to Desktop Enviroment">​</a></h4><p>A desktop environment bundles together a variety of components to provide common graphical user interface elements such as icons, toolbars, wallpapers, and desktop widgets. Additionally, most desktop environments include a set of integrated applications and utilities. Most importantly, desktop environments provide their own window manager, which can however usually be replaced with another compatible one.</p><p>The user is free to configure their GUI environment in any number of ways. Desktop environments simply provide a complete and convenient means of accomplishing this task.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="whats-next">What's Next?<a href="#whats-next" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's Next?" title="Direct link to What's Next?">​</a></h2><p>After reading this blog, you must have gotten the basic understanding of what GNU/Linux is, what linux itself is, and what a linux distribution is, and what it does. Moving on from here, you can dive deep and understand in depth how each component decsribed in the blog post work. For example, how does a typical linux file system look like. The world of operating systems is vast, and only so much can be covered in one blog post.
Keep asking questions, and keep reading!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>linux</category>
            <category>cli</category>
            <category>terminal</category>
            <category>tui</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[General Posting Guidelines]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/blog-posting-guidelines</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/blog-posting-guidelines</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[General Posting Guidelines]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="welcome-to-our-first-blog">Welcome to our first blog<a href="#welcome-to-our-first-blog" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Welcome to our first blog" title="Direct link to Welcome to our first blog">​</a></h2><p>Welcome everyone to TCET Open Source's Blog Section. Here, we promote blogging in the student community. Talk about ongoing trends in tech, student life at TCET, and any topic you feel would feel great for this blog.</p><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note alert alert--secondary admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>note</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>This particular blog will have recurring adjustments. Last revised on Oct 1st, 2023.</p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="general-blog-guidlines">General Blog Guidlines<a href="#general-blog-guidlines" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to General Blog Guidlines" title="Direct link to General Blog Guidlines">​</a></h2><p>Here we define all the basic guidlines a blog should follow in TCET Open Source Blogs.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="clone-the-project">Clone the project<a href="#clone-the-project" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Clone the project" title="Direct link to Clone the project">​</a></h3><p>For being able to contribute anywhere, one must be able to clone and run projects. You can visit this <a href="https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/docs/projects/docs-site/getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tutorial</a> to learn how to work on this project.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="basic-github-commands">Basic GitHub commands<a href="#basic-github-commands" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Basic GitHub commands" title="Direct link to Basic GitHub commands">​</a></h3><p>For any contributor it is very necessary to understand basic GitHub commands to begin with. There is a <em>resources forum</em> on <strong>TCET - Open Source Discord server</strong> where you can find relevant references for the same. There can also be a blog post regarding these commands in the future!</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="understand-file-structure">Understand file structure<a href="#understand-file-structure" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understand file structure" title="Direct link to Understand file structure">​</a></h3><p>Once you have cloned the project in your local storage, you will need to perform the following:</p><ol><li>Open the project directory and navigate to <code>blog/</code>.</li><li>Create a folder for your blog post.</li></ol><ul><li>The folder should have the following name format:</li></ul><div class="language-sh codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-sh codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">yyyy-mm-dd-blog-title</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><ul><li>Here, the date stands for the date when the post is supposed to be released. The blog title should be relevant to the content within the post.</li></ul><ol start="3"><li>Within the folder, create <code>index.mdx</code>. This file will serve as a text document where you can format your content which will reflect in the final post.</li></ol><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="understand-markdown-files-and-syntax">Understand markdown files and syntax<a href="#understand-markdown-files-and-syntax" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understand markdown files and syntax" title="Direct link to Understand markdown files and syntax">​</a></h3><p>Markdown is a lightweight markup language that you can use to add formatting elements to plaintext text documents. The <code>index.mdx</code> file created in your blog folder is a markdown file, similar to how <em>index.html</em> can be an HTML file. It is very essential for a blog contributor to understand the basic syntax of markdown. <em>Resource forum</em> in our <strong><a href="https://discord.com/invite/r7ZhAREg2M" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord server</a></strong> covers basic syntax of these files.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="first-steps">First steps<a href="#first-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First steps" title="Direct link to First steps">​</a></h3><p>Before moving any further, a blogger must know the following:</p><blockquote><ul><li><code>slug</code> - It is the last part of the URL address that serves as a unique identifier of the blog post.</li><li><code>title</code> - The main title of the blog post. Note that the blog title should be relevant to the content within the post.</li><li><code>authors</code> - The list of authors who have worked on the blog post. Look below to understand how to add authors.</li><li><code>tags</code> - It highlights the key words of the post to boost it's visibility on the internet and improve the SEO.</li></ul></blockquote><p>These four information are necessary to be present in every post. Without these, no posts will be approved and merged within the blog.</p><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info alert alert--info admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>Mention Authors</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>Authors can be added in two ways.</p><ul><li>Internally in <code>index.mdx</code> (recommended, for outside organization contributors)</li><li>In the <code>authors.yml</code> file. (<strong>TCET Open Source Members only</strong>)</li></ul><p>If you are not a member of the organization, you can simply append your author(s) in the following way:</p><div class="language-mdx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-mdx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">authors:</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  - name: Name of Author 1</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    title: Designation, Post or About</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    url: https://github.com/author1</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    image_url: https://github.com/author1.png</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  - name: Name of Author 2</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    title: Designation, Post or About</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    url: https://github.com/author1</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    image_url: https://github.com/author2.png</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="important-things-to-take-note-of">Important things to take note of:<a href="#important-things-to-take-note-of" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Important things to take note of:" title="Direct link to Important things to take note of:">​</a></h4><ul><li><code>url:</code> can also be an authors' personal website or portfolio.</li><li><code>image_url:</code> requires a user to have a profile pic on their Github Account. We recommend to append a Github Profile Icon.</li></ul></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="adding-images">Adding images<a href="#adding-images" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Adding images" title="Direct link to Adding images">​</a></h3><p>Tired of good ol' <em>textbook nerdy</em> look on your post? Introducing: <strong>images</strong>. Images are a great way to keep the reader's attention to your posts, and now you can do that very easily:</p><ol><li>The image must be present within your blog folder. If it isn't, save the image in your blog folder.</li><li>To add the image within your post, use the following syntax:</li></ol><div class="language-mdx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-mdx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">![Alt text](image.png)</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><ul><li>Here, <code>image.png</code> stands for the name of the image you have in the blog directory. Markdown supports a great amount of image formats, ranging from png, jpg, svg, and even gifs.</li></ul><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note alert alert--secondary admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>WONDERING</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>Is gif pronounced <em>gif</em> or <em>jif</em>? Something to ponder upon.</p></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="utilizing-truncate">Utilizing truncate<a href="#utilizing-truncate" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Utilizing truncate" title="Direct link to Utilizing truncate">​</a></h3><p>Many bloggers have many different ways to write their blogs. Many start off with a nice paragraph, some start off with images, and some do both! All blogging practices are welcome in the Organization. However it is important to <strong>truncate</strong>.</p><p>Truncate is a custom breakpoint introduced in the blog to identify how much part of the blog should be visible in the feed. It cuts off the rest of the blog which can be read further by opening the blog itself. Here's a good example of how to use it:</p><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info alert alert--info admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>This is a blogpost</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><div class="language-mdx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-mdx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">Hello and welcome to my blogpost.</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">Today we will be covering everything you can imagine! </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">JAM Stack, Web3, ML, Data Science, my favourite food, Cybersecurity, and much more. </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">Sounds like a hefty lot, and it would be embarassing to flood out the entire blogs feed. </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">This might be a decent place to cut the rest of the blog out!</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">&lt;!--truncate--&gt;</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">Here's where the rest of the blog content goes</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div></div></div><p>Hence in the output, only the above paragraph is visible on the feed. The rest of the blog would be visible once the viewer opens your blog.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="congratulations">Congratulations<a href="#congratulations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Congratulations" title="Direct link to Congratulations">​</a></h3><p>Following these steps and points, you will be able to create a beautiful blog post. It's final structure would look something like this:</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="/assets/images/structure-8689f7412f51f4deda8726b490473caa.png" width="873" height="210" class="img_ev3q"></p><p><em>With a fresh blog post ready, you can now finally create a pull request to reflect your post on our blog here!</em></p><p>Looking forward to new content from you all. Have fun and go contribute something great!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>free</category>
            <category>open</category>
            <category>source</category>
            <category>software</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Exploring the Future of Gaming- Cloud Gaming Unveiled]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/Cloud-gaming</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/Cloud-gaming</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Hey there, fellow gamers! Today, we're diving into the fascinating world of cloud gaming, a technology that's changing the way we play and enjoy our favorite titles. In this article, we'll break down the concept of cloud gaming, its evolution, and its promising future.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hey there, fellow gamers! Today, we're diving into the fascinating world of <strong>cloud gaming</strong>, a technology that's changing the way we play and enjoy our favorite titles. In this article, we'll break down the concept of cloud gaming, its evolution, and its promising future.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction-to-cloud-gaming">Introduction to Cloud Gaming<a href="#introduction-to-cloud-gaming" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction to Cloud Gaming" title="Direct link to Introduction to Cloud Gaming">​</a></h2><p>Imagine playing high-quality video games without the <em>need</em> for expensive gaming hardware or the hassle of <em>downloading and installing massive game files</em>. That's the magic of cloud gaming! It's like Netflix for gamers, where you can instantly access and play games over the internet without worrying about hardware requirements.</p><p>Most modern games demand a hefty amount of storage space and powerful hardware to run smoothly. Think about titles like Call of Duty's Warzone, which takes up over 1000GB of storage. To play these games with the best experience, you'd need a high-end PC or gaming console. But what if there was a more affordable alternative?</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cloud Gaming Demonstration by playing Cyberpunk 2077 on mobile" src="/assets/images/image-3c83b87da0f4193ef12ce76473b76e07.png" width="433" height="229" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="how-cloud-gaming-works">How Cloud Gaming Works<a href="#how-cloud-gaming-works" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How Cloud Gaming Works" title="Direct link to How Cloud Gaming Works">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cloud Gaming flow" src="/assets/images/image2-71b6f0bc3eb608f73a3c0b0b1fcf5aaf.png" width="800" height="400" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Cloud gaming operates within the realm of cloud computing. Instead of storing game files on your local device, they're hosted and processed on powerful remote servers in data centers. Here's how it works in a nutshell:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Remote Servers</strong>: Powerful servers host and run the games, eliminating the need for you to download and install them on your device.</p></li><li><p><strong>Streaming Gameplay</strong>: Similar to streaming services like Netflix, cloud gaming sends a video stream of the gameplay over the internet to your device.</p></li><li><p><strong>Input Control</strong>: Your inputs (the buttons you press and the moves you make) are sent to the server, where the game responds accordingly. This allows you to play even on low-end devices.</p></li></ul><p>While cloud gaming offers incredible convenience, it's important to note that it can introduce some input lag, depending on factors like your internet connection stability and the distance between you and the server.</p><p><em>Cloud Gaming is one of the Best Examples to showcase the power of Cloud Computing.</em></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-history-and-future-of-cloud-gaming">The History and Future of Cloud Gaming<a href="#the-history-and-future-of-cloud-gaming" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The History and Future of Cloud Gaming" title="Direct link to The History and Future of Cloud Gaming">​</a></h2><p>In the past, cloud gaming faced numerous challenges, including network issues. Google's attempt with Google Stadia was ambitious but struggled due to connectivity problems. Other giants like Amazon and Microsoft also entered the arena with Amazon Luna and Xbox cloud gaming.</p><p>However, the future of cloud gaming looks bright, especially in countries like India. Gaming is growing rapidly, and cloud gaming provides an affordable platform for those unable to invest in high-end gaming hardware. The potential to earn rewards through gaming is also on the rise, further boosting its popularity.</p><p>The primary challenge facing cloud gaming today is network-related issues, but providers are actively working on solutions to make it accessible to more users.</p><p>We can say Cloud Gaming was just the first step for the cloud computing service to even non-tech users.
Google is developing &amp; testing Cloud Quantum computing so that one day everyone can access the Incredible power of Quantum computers without the need for a quantum rig, which might be bigger than most of our houses.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="cloud quantum computing" src="/assets/images/image3-b19f0a908a4a95fe6596e31a03295ba3.png" width="4100" height="2293" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="advantages-and-drawbacks-of-cloud-gaming">Advantages and Drawbacks of Cloud Gaming<a href="#advantages-and-drawbacks-of-cloud-gaming" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Advantages and Drawbacks of Cloud Gaming" title="Direct link to Advantages and Drawbacks of Cloud Gaming">​</a></h2><p>Cloud gaming offers several advantages, including:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Universal Platform</strong>: You can play games on any device with an internet connection, from consoles to smartphones.</p></li><li><p><strong>Cost-Efficiency</strong>: No need for expensive hardware, as the processing is done on remote servers.</p></li><li><p><strong>Portability</strong>: Play on the go without worrying about installation and setup.</p></li></ul><p>However, it's not without its drawbacks:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Internet Dependency</strong>: A stable internet connection is crucial for a smooth experience.</p></li><li><p><strong>Input Lag</strong>: Some games may suffer from input delay due to server processing.</p></li><li><p><strong>Limited Awareness</strong>: Many people are still unaware of cloud gaming, and few providers exist compared to traditional gaming options.</p></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="current-status-of-cloud-gaming">Current Status of Cloud Gaming<a href="#current-status-of-cloud-gaming" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Current Status of Cloud Gaming" title="Direct link to Current Status of Cloud Gaming">​</a></h2><p>Several cloud gaming services are making waves in the industry:</p><ul class="contains-task-list containsTaskList_mC6p"><li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" checked="" disabled=""> <strong>Nvidia GeForce Now</strong>: This service is known for its low system requirements, compatibility with various devices, and a free trial period.</li><li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" checked="" disabled=""> <strong>XBox Game Cloud</strong>: Known for Various game titles for free to play in the subscription of Game Pass.</li><li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" checked="" disabled=""> <strong>JioGames Cloud</strong>: Building the Cloud gaming culture &amp; infrastructure in India at a reasonable rate.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="is-cloud-gaming-worth-it">Is Cloud Gaming Worth It?<a href="#is-cloud-gaming-worth-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Is Cloud Gaming Worth It?" title="Direct link to Is Cloud Gaming Worth It?">​</a></h2><p>While cloud gaming shows immense potential, it's still in its early stages. Input lag and connectivity issues can be frustrating, especially for competitive gamers. Traditional gaming setups remain a popular choice. However, as technology advances, cloud gaming has the potential to become the future of gaming in the coming decade.</p><p>In conclusion, cloud gaming is a game-changer with the potential to democratize gaming by making it accessible to more players. As it evolves and overcomes its current challenges, we can expect cloud gaming to reshape the gaming landscape in the near future.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="references">References:<a href="#references" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to References:" title="Direct link to References:">​</a></h2><ul><li><a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/geforce-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nvidia GeForce Now</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PlayStation_Now" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PlayStation Now</a></li><li>~Google Stadia~ (closed right now)</li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>cloud</category>
            <category>gaming</category>
            <category>cyberpunk</category>
            <category>nvidia</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This Month in AI - June 2023]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-june-2023</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-june-2023</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Latest News & Breakthroughs in the Month of Kuly 2023 in AI/ML/DS.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="A robotic hand touching a speck of light" src="/assets/images/tmai-june23-poster-55cb113cecc705d1a7fe526fd49f590f.png" width="1587" height="2245" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="code-optimization-revolutionized-google-deepminds-ai-unleashes-new-speed-boosting-technique-">Code Optimization Revolutionized: Google DeepMind's AI Unleashes New Speed-Boosting Technique. <sup id="fnref-1-3c289c"><a href="#fn-1-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup><a href="#code-optimization-revolutionized-google-deepminds-ai-unleashes-new-speed-boosting-technique-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to code-optimization-revolutionized-google-deepminds-ai-unleashes-new-speed-boosting-technique-" title="Direct link to code-optimization-revolutionized-google-deepminds-ai-unleashes-new-speed-boosting-technique-">​</a></h2><p>DeepMind's AlphaDev AI achieves groundbreaking speed improvements in sorting algorithms, surpassing existing methods by up to 70%. Its innovative techniques have been adopted by millions of software developers, marking the first integration of AI-discovered algorithms in language updates. DeepMind's gamified approach, using reinforcement learning, trains AlphaDev to construct faster and correct algorithms. This breakthrough revolutionizes code optimization and sets the stage for further AI-driven innovations in computer science.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="elevating-the-shopping-experience-with-ai-virtual-try-on-on-google-shopping-">Elevating the Shopping Experience with AI Virtual Try-On on Google Shopping. <sup id="fnref-2-3c289c"><a href="#fn-2-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup><a href="#elevating-the-shopping-experience-with-ai-virtual-try-on-on-google-shopping-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to elevating-the-shopping-experience-with-ai-virtual-try-on-on-google-shopping-" title="Direct link to elevating-the-shopping-experience-with-ai-virtual-try-on-on-google-shopping-">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Example of Virtual Try of Clothes with AI" src="/assets/images/virtual-try-9c7beabc833d706d5ad3398b7e5c7f6e.png" width="1000" height="500" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Google Shopping has introduced AI Virtual Try-On, a new feature that allows users to virtually try on beauty products before buying them. Using advanced machine learning algorithms and facial recognition technology, the feature provides realistic representations of the products on the user's face. It enhances convenience, addresses concerns about online shopping, and offers a seamless experience. Users can access the feature from Google Search, Google Shopping, or participating retailer websites, making informed decisions with detailed product information and user reviews. This innovation bridges the gap between online and in-store try-ons, revolutionizing the beauty shopping experience.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ink-ai-unveils-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-for-effortless-full-length-e-book-creation-">Ink AI Unveils ChatGPT-Based E-book Generator for Effortless Full-Length E-book Creation. <sup id="fnref-3-3c289c"><a href="#fn-3-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup><a href="#ink-ai-unveils-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-for-effortless-full-length-e-book-creation-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ink-ai-unveils-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-for-effortless-full-length-e-book-creation-" title="Direct link to ink-ai-unveils-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-for-effortless-full-length-e-book-creation-">​</a></h2><p>Ink AI has introduced a game-changing e-book generator tool that utilizes ChatGPT, an AI language model, to effortlessly create full-length e-books. By inputting prompts, users receive context-aware responses that form the basis of their e-books, making the writing process faster and more efficient. The tool allows customization of genre, style, and length, and the user-friendly interface simplifies content creation. Ink AI's e-book generator opens up new possibilities for authors, content creators, and publishers by revolutionizing the e-book creation process with AI technology.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="meta-unveils-stablediffusion-a-groundbreaking-ai-model-for-music-generation-">Meta Unveils Stablediffusion: A Groundbreaking AI Model for Music Generation. <sup id="fnref-4-3c289c"><a href="#fn-4-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">4</a></sup><a href="#meta-unveils-stablediffusion-a-groundbreaking-ai-model-for-music-generation-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to meta-unveils-stablediffusion-a-groundbreaking-ai-model-for-music-generation-" title="Direct link to meta-unveils-stablediffusion-a-groundbreaking-ai-model-for-music-generation-">​</a></h2><p>Meta has introduced Stablediffusion, an advanced AI model called MusicGen, designed for music generation. Unlike traditional models, Stablediffusion produces stable, coherent, and emotionally engaging musical compositions. Trained on diverse musical genres, the model incorporates stability mechanisms for smooth transitions and consistent structures. </p><p>It considers melody, harmonies, rhythms, and tonal variations, resulting in natural and professional-sounding compositions. Stablediffusion offers a powerful tool for musicians, composers, and music enthusiasts, revolutionizing AI-generated music with its stable and artistically satisfying output.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="draggan-goes-open-source-empowering-developers-with-advanced-ai-framework-">Draggan Goes Open Source: Empowering Developers with Advanced AI Framework. <sup id="fnref-5-3c289c"><a href="#fn-5-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">5</a></sup><a href="#draggan-goes-open-source-empowering-developers-with-advanced-ai-framework-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to draggan-goes-open-source-empowering-developers-with-advanced-ai-framework-" title="Direct link to draggan-goes-open-source-empowering-developers-with-advanced-ai-framework-">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Example of DragGAN to change perspective of Lion and more" src="/assets/images/draggan-5e9ce415a7e679b61439b03be2a1708e.jpeg" width="2048" height="1024" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Draggan, an advanced AI framework focused on reinforcement learning, has been released as open source. This allows developers worldwide to access and utilize its capabilities for training AI models. Draggan simplifies the process with its user-friendly interface, extensive documentation, and pre-built components, enabling faster development and deployment of AI systems. By democratizing access to this powerful tool, the open-source release of Draggan promotes collaboration and accelerates advancements in AI research and application development.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="mit-introduces-new-model-for-accelerated-drug-discovery-">MIT Introduces New Model for Accelerated Drug Discovery. <sup id="fnref-6-3c289c"><a href="#fn-6-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">6</a></sup><a href="#mit-introduces-new-model-for-accelerated-drug-discovery-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to mit-introduces-new-model-for-accelerated-drug-discovery-" title="Direct link to mit-introduces-new-model-for-accelerated-drug-discovery-">​</a></h2><p>MIT researchers have developed a groundbreaking AI model called AccelerateDrug, which revolutionizes the process of drug discovery. The model utilizes advanced machine learning algorithms to rapidly analyze chemical and biological data, predicting the effectiveness of potential drug compounds. By significantly reducing experimentation time and resources, AccelerateDrug streamlines the drug discovery process and expedites the development of new medications. </p><p>The model has demonstrated high accuracy and outperformed existing methods in predicting drug efficacy. AccelerateDrug has the potential to accelerate the availability of life-saving treatments, benefiting patients and advancing healthcare outcomes.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="google-introduces-audiopalm-bridging-the-gap-between-text-and-voice-">Google Introduces AudioPalm: Bridging the Gap between Text and Voice. <sup id="fnref-7-3c289c"><a href="#fn-7-3c289c" class="footnote-ref">7</a></sup><a href="#google-introduces-audiopalm-bridging-the-gap-between-text-and-voice-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to google-introduces-audiopalm-bridging-the-gap-between-text-and-voice-" title="Direct link to google-introduces-audiopalm-bridging-the-gap-between-text-and-voice-">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Brief Architecture of AudioPaLM" src="/assets/images/audiopalm-718317081c702f240d7f418279678d17.png" width="1536" height="528" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Google has introduced AudioPalm, an innovative technology that bridges the gap between text and voice. Using advanced AI algorithms, it converts written text into human-like speech and transcribes spoken language into written text accurately. AudioPalm enhances accessibility, user experiences, and content creation, benefiting individuals with visual impairments and those seeking a more immersive interaction. </p><p>The technology has applications in education, entertainment, and accessibility services, and it integrates with existing Google services like Google Assistant and Google Translate. Google's AudioPalm represents a significant advancement in natural language processing, enabling seamless conversion between text and voice for enhanced user experiences.</p><div class="footnotes"><hr><ol><li id="fn-1-3c289c"><a href="https://www.deepmind.com/research/highlighted-research/alphago" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.deepmind.com/research/highlighted-research/alphago</a><a href="#fnref-1-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-2-3c289c"><a href="https://blog.google/products/shopping/ai-virtual-try-on-google-shopping/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://blog.google/products/shopping/ai-virtual-try-on-google-shopping/</a><a href="#fnref-2-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-3-3c289c"><a href="https://goodereader.com/blog/e-book-news/new-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-tool-from-ink-ai-can-create-full-length-e-books-easily" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://goodereader.com/blog/e-book-news/new-chatgpt-based-e-book-generator-tool-from-ink-ai-can-create-full-length-e-books-easily</a><a href="#fnref-3-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-4-3c289c"><a href="https://analyticsindiamag.com/meta-releases-stablediffusion-for-music-musicgen/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://analyticsindiamag.com/meta-releases-stablediffusion-for-music-musicgen/</a><a href="#fnref-4-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-5-3c289c"><a href="https://analyticsindiamag.com/draggan-is-finally-open-source/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://analyticsindiamag.com/draggan-is-finally-open-source/</a><a href="#fnref-5-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-6-3c289c"><a href="https://news.mit.edu/2023/new-model-offers-speedy-drug-discovery-0608" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://news.mit.edu/2023/new-model-offers-speedy-drug-discovery-0608</a><a href="#fnref-6-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-7-3c289c"><a href="https://google-research.github.io/seanet/audiopalm/examples/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://google-research.github.io/seanet/audiopalm/examples/</a><a href="#fnref-7-3c289c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li></ol></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>mind-benders</category>
            <category>ai</category>
            <category>tmai</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introduction to APIs: Unlocking the Power of Integration]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/introduction-to-api</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/introduction-to-api</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[An Introduction to APIs: Unlocking the Power of Integration]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><em>Applications and systems rely on smooth communication and data sharing to deliver improved functionality and services in today's interconnected digital environment. <strong>Application Programming Interfaces (APIs)</strong> are quite important in this situation. APIs serve as mediators, enabling interoperability, data sharing, and communication between various software programmes. This article will provide you a thorough introduction to APIs and their importance in contemporary software development, whether you're a developer, a tech enthusiast, or just interested about the world of APIs.</em></p></blockquote><br><figure><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/api-to-layman-87f159cbade040856e308df80d0e089a.png" style="border:2px solid grey" class="img_ev3q"><center><figcaption>APIs to a layman</figcaption></center></figure><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction-to-api">Introduction to API<a href="#introduction-to-api" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction to API" title="Direct link to Introduction to API">​</a></h2><p><strong>Application Programming Interface</strong> is referred to as API. It is a set of guidelines and protocols that specifies how various software components ought to communicate and share information. </p><ul><li><strong>APIs</strong> can be thought of as a contract that enables successful communication between two software entities. </li><li><strong>APIs</strong> give programmers a standardised method of using the features of other software platforms, libraries, or systems.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-are-apis-important">Why are APIs Important?<a href="#why-are-apis-important" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why are APIs Important?" title="Direct link to Why are APIs Important?">​</a></h2><p>APIs have revolutionized the way software is developed and integrated. Here are some key reasons why APIs are important:</p><div class="tabs-container tabList__CuJ"><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal" class="tabs"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true" class="tabs__item tabItem_LNqP unique_cziY tabs__item--active">Seamless Integration</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false" class="tabs__item tabItem_LNqP unique_cziY">Extensibility and Scalability</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false" class="tabs__item tabItem_LNqP unique_cziY">Collaboration and Innovation</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false" class="tabs__item tabItem_LNqP unique_cziY">User Experience</li></ul><div class="margin-top--md"><div role="tabpanel" class="tabItem_Ymn6"><p>By allowing various software systems to interact and cooperate, APIs enable developers to take advantage of already-existing functions and resources without having to start from scratch.</p></div><div role="tabpanel" class="tabItem_Ymn6" hidden=""><p>APIs give software developers a modular way to create new features, services, or data sources. As applications can be built upon existing APIs, promoting extensibility and scalability while saving time and effort.</p></div><div role="tabpanel" class="tabItem_Ymn6" hidden=""><p>By offering a standardised method of sharing data and services, APIs promote collaboration between developers and organisations. As a result, innovation is accelerated since developers can use APIs to build new apps or incorporate current systems into creative solutions.</p></div><div role="tabpanel" class="tabItem_Ymn6" hidden=""><p>APIs make it easier to incorporate services or data sources from outside sources into applications, which improves the overall user experience. For instance, incorporating a weather API into a travel app gives users access to real-time weather information, enhancing the utility and appeal of the service.</p></div></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="types-of-apis">Types of APIs<a href="#types-of-apis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of APIs" title="Direct link to Types of APIs">​</a></h2><p>APIs come in different types and formats, depending on the purpose and underlying technology. Here are some common types of APIs:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Web APIs:</strong> These APIs allow web-based services and applications to communicate with one another. The majority of the time, they are built on widely used web protocols like <code>HTTP</code> and <code>REST</code> (Representational State Transfer).</p></li><li><p><strong>SOAP APIs:</strong> Based on XML (eXtensible Markup Language), SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol) APIs offer a standardised method for applications to communicate structured information across a network.</p></li><li><p><strong>JSON-RPC and XML-RPC:</strong> JSON (JavaScript Object Notation) or XML can be used as the data format for remote procedure calls when using the <code>JSON-RPC</code> or <code>XML-RPC APIs</code>. They're frequently employed for lightweight.</p></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="api-communication-styles">API Communication Styles:<a href="#api-communication-styles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to API Communication Styles:" title="Direct link to API Communication Styles:">​</a></h2><ul><li><p><strong>RESTful APIs:</strong> REST (Representational State Transfer) is a popular architectural style for designing web APIs. RESTful APIs use standard HTTP methods such as <code>GET</code>, <code>POST</code>, <code>PUT</code>, and <code>DELETE</code> to perform operations on resources. They often return data in formats like JSON or XML.</p></li><li><p><strong>GraphQL:</strong> GraphQL is an alternative to RESTful APIs that provides a more flexible and efficient approach to data retrieval. With GraphQL, clients can specify the exact data they need, reducing over-fetching and under-fetching of data.</p></li><li><p><strong>Real-Time APIs:</strong> Real-time APIs use technologies like WebSockets to enable bidirectional communication between the client and the server. They are ideal for applications that require instant updates, such as chat applications or real-time collaboration tools.</p></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="common-apis">Common APIs<a href="#common-apis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Common APIs" title="Direct link to Common APIs">​</a></h2><ul><li><p><strong>Social media APIs:</strong> Websites like <strong><a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitter</a></strong>, and <strong><a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/instagram-api/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram</a></strong> offer APIs that let programmers incorporate social media features into their applications, such as updating statuses, retrieving user profiles, or engaging with social networks.</p></li><li><p><strong>Payment Gateway APIs:</strong> Companies such as <strong><a href="https://developer.paypal.com/api/rest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PayPal</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://stripe.com/docs/api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stripe</a></strong>, and <strong><a href="https://developer.paypal.com/braintree/docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Braintree</a></strong> provide APIs for handling online payments, allowing developers to include secure payment processing into their apps.</p></li><li><p><strong>Mapping and Geolocation APIs:</strong> Maps, geolocation data, routing, and other location-based services are all made available by mapping and geolocation APIs, which developers can use to build apps with mapping features. Examples of these APIs include <strong><a href="https://developers.google.com/maps/apis-by-platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Maps</a></strong> and <strong><a href="https://docs.mapbox.com/api/overview/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mapbox</a></strong>.</p></li></ul><img loading="lazy" src="/assets/images/apis-b58fc05e4054c5413c8f5ac058e3fc9a.png" class="img_ev3q"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>APIs enable seamless integration, teamwork, and creativity, serving as the foundation for contemporary software development. For developers and organisations wishing to take use of the power of APIs to build strong and interconnected applications, understanding APIs and their many types, communication styles, authentication methods, documentation practises, and management systems is essential. So go ahead and discover the immense possibilities that APIs contain for your software applications by exploring their enormous world!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>api</category>
            <category>integration</category>
            <category>software</category>
            <category>authentication</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This Month in AI - May 2023]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-may-2023</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-may-2023</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Latest News & Breakthroughs in the Month of May 2023 in AI/ML/DS.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="A robotic hand touching a speck of light" src="/assets/images/tmai-may23-poster-72d8b140c6460d0c90952c8d11ee5a8a.png" width="794" height="794" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="googles-palm-2-revolutionizing-language-modeling-with-multilingual-proficiency-reasoning-abilities-and-coding-proficiency-">Google's PaLM 2: Revolutionizing Language Modeling with Multilingual Proficiency, Reasoning Abilities, and Coding Proficiency. <sup id="fnref-1-d9f119"><a href="#fn-1-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup><a href="#googles-palm-2-revolutionizing-language-modeling-with-multilingual-proficiency-reasoning-abilities-and-coding-proficiency-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to googles-palm-2-revolutionizing-language-modeling-with-multilingual-proficiency-reasoning-abilities-and-coding-proficiency-" title="Direct link to googles-palm-2-revolutionizing-language-modeling-with-multilingual-proficiency-reasoning-abilities-and-coding-proficiency-">​</a></h2><p>Discover the cutting-edge advancements in AI from Google as they unveil PaLM 2, their next-generation language model. PaLM 2 has undergone extensive training on multilingual text, enabling it to understand, generate, and translate nuanced language across more than 100 languages. With improved reasoning capabilities and proficiency in programming languages, PaLM 2 demonstrates its potential for logic, common sense reasoning, mathematics, and coding tasks.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="An Example of Prompt to Med PaLM - A specialized PaLM Model" src="/assets/images/med-palm-dc4977b-b9d9d35908d694861628347594340abc.png" width="700" height="339" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Google has already integrated PaLM 2 into over 25 products and features, empowering users worldwide with enhanced language generation, efficient workspace features, and productivity tools. Through the development of PaLM 2, Google continues to drive innovation in AI and deliver real-world benefits in areas like healthcare and creative endeavors.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="metas-ai-breakthrough-speech-recognition-for-1000-languages-now-open-source-paving-the-way-for-language-preservation-and-universal-communication-">Meta's AI breakthrough: Speech recognition for 1,000+ languages now open source, paving the way for language preservation and universal communication. <sup id="fnref-2-d9f119"><a href="#fn-2-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup><a href="#metas-ai-breakthrough-speech-recognition-for-1000-languages-now-open-source-paving-the-way-for-language-preservation-and-universal-communication-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to metas-ai-breakthrough-speech-recognition-for-1000-languages-now-open-source-paving-the-way-for-language-preservation-and-universal-communication-" title="Direct link to metas-ai-breakthrough-speech-recognition-for-1000-languages-now-open-source-paving-the-way-for-language-preservation-and-universal-communication-">​</a></h2><p>Meta's AI breakthrough empowers speech recognition in over 1,000 languages, a significant leap towards preserving endangered languages. The company is sharing these models as open source on GitHub, enabling developers to build inclusive speech applications for diverse languages. Existing speech recognition models cover a mere fraction of the world's 7,000 languages due to limited labeled training data. Meta overcame this challenge by retraining their AI model to learn speech patterns from audio, requiring minimal data. Their models can converse in over 1,000 languages and recognize more than 4,000, with half the error rate compared to rival models. While there are risks of mistranscription and biased words, Meta's advancements have far-reaching implications for language preservation and global communication.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ai-revolutionizes-antibiotic-discovery-unveiling-a-breakthrough-against-hospital-superbugs-">AI Revolutionizes Antibiotic Discovery: Unveiling a Breakthrough Against Hospital Superbugs. <sup id="fnref-3-d9f119"><a href="#fn-3-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup><a href="#ai-revolutionizes-antibiotic-discovery-unveiling-a-breakthrough-against-hospital-superbugs-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ai-revolutionizes-antibiotic-discovery-unveiling-a-breakthrough-against-hospital-superbugs-" title="Direct link to ai-revolutionizes-antibiotic-discovery-unveiling-a-breakthrough-against-hospital-superbugs-">​</a></h2><p>Scientists from McMaster University have utilised artificial intelligence (AI) to uncover a breakthrough antibiotic called abaucin, which shows promising potential in combating drug-resistant infections, particularly Acinetobacter baumannii. This bacterium poses a significant threat in hospitals and is known to cause severe conditions like pneumonia and meningitis. </p><p>The traditional methods of antibiotic discovery have proven challenging and time-consuming. However, AI algorithms allowed researchers to swiftly assess millions of molecules, leading to the identification of abaucin. Unlike broad-spectrum antibiotics, abaucin specifically targets A. baumannii, reducing the risk of drug resistance development and opening doors to more precise and effective treatments. This study underscores the immense potential of AI in revolutionising antibiotic discovery and providing hope in the fight against deadly hospital superbugs.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="unleash-your-creativity-photoshops-ai-transforms-your-images-with-a-single-text-prompt-">Unleash Your Creativity: Photoshop's AI Transforms Your Images with a Single Text Prompt. <sup id="fnref-4-d9f119"><a href="#fn-4-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">4</a></sup><a href="#unleash-your-creativity-photoshops-ai-transforms-your-images-with-a-single-text-prompt-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to unleash-your-creativity-photoshops-ai-transforms-your-images-with-a-single-text-prompt-" title="Direct link to unleash-your-creativity-photoshops-ai-transforms-your-images-with-a-single-text-prompt-">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="A before &amp;amp; after image of dog after applying Generative Fill of Photoshop" src="/assets/images/photoshop-bf49f54051f997bbf340ba6b0f67879d.png" width="990" height="743" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Adobe has introduced a groundbreaking AI tool called Generative Fill in its Photoshop application, leveraging generative AI to add or remove objects from photos based on a simple text prompt. Acting as an "AI co-pilot," Adobe Firefly powers this feature, aiming to revolutionize the photo editing process. While enhancing user creativity, Adobe acknowledges the need to address concerns about potential misuse of the technology. The addition of Generative Fill is expected to usher in a new era of AI-driven creativity in the creative industries, providing extraordinary results and streamlining previously time-consuming tasks. Currently available in the beta version, a wider release of this transformative AI tool in Photoshop is on the horizon.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="safeguarding-the-digital-frontier-exploring-the-reality-of-ai-in-cybersecurity-">Safeguarding the Digital Frontier: Exploring the Reality of AI in Cybersecurity. <sup id="fnref-5-d9f119"><a href="#fn-5-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">5</a></sup><a href="#safeguarding-the-digital-frontier-exploring-the-reality-of-ai-in-cybersecurity-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to safeguarding-the-digital-frontier-exploring-the-reality-of-ai-in-cybersecurity-" title="Direct link to safeguarding-the-digital-frontier-exploring-the-reality-of-ai-in-cybersecurity-">​</a></h2><p>In the realm of cybersecurity, the long-awaited promise of artificial intelligence (AI) is becoming a reality. AI-driven capabilities have evolved from simple rule-based systems to sophisticated tools that leverage generative AI and contextualise vast amounts of data. This breakthrough empowers cybersecurity teams with game-changing speed and accuracy, providing them with a much-needed advantage in their ongoing battle against cybercriminals. With a skills shortage and data explosion posing challenges, matured AI capabilities address these obstacles by automating tasks, improving defence postures, and enabling precise actions. </p><p>By combining AI with automation, security teams can achieve reliable speed and enhance their ability to detect, investigate, and respond to threats. The integration of AI into threat detection and response technologies, such as IBM's QRadar Suite, amplifies the effectiveness of security operations centres (SOCs) and streamlines the incident lifecycle. With AI's assistance, SOC teams can prioritise real threats amidst the noise, accelerate investigation and response processes, and significantly enhance overall resilience and readiness in the cybersecurity industry.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="spotifys-potential-ai-breakthrough-ai-generated-podcast-ads-">Spotify's Potential AI Breakthrough: AI-Generated Podcast Ads. <sup id="fnref-6-d9f119"><a href="#fn-6-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">6</a></sup><a href="#spotifys-potential-ai-breakthrough-ai-generated-podcast-ads-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to spotifys-potential-ai-breakthrough-ai-generated-podcast-ads-" title="Direct link to spotifys-potential-ai-breakthrough-ai-generated-podcast-ads-">​</a></h2><p>In a recent podcast episode, Bill Simmons shared that Spotify is reportedly working on AI technology that would allow podcast hosts to create host-read ads without having to personally record them. This development could offer podcasters exciting opportunities, including the creation of geo-targeted and multilingual ads, while saving valuable time for content creation. Although Spotify has not officially confirmed these claims, their ongoing investment in AI technology, exemplified by the introduction of AI DJ, suggests the possibility. </p><p>The advent of AI-generated podcast ads would revolutionise the industry, offering podcasters a time-saving alternative and the potential to reach a broader audience. However, concerns regarding authenticity and the risk of misinformation should also be considered. The development of AI-generated podcast ads marks a significant milestone in podcasting, with the future implementation and audience response eagerly anticipated.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="chegg-vs-chatgpt-the-battle-for-ai-powered-education-dominance-">Chegg vs. ChatGPT: The Battle for AI-Powered Education Dominance. <sup id="fnref-7-d9f119"><a href="#fn-7-d9f119" class="footnote-ref">7</a></sup><a href="#chegg-vs-chatgpt-the-battle-for-ai-powered-education-dominance-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to chegg-vs-chatgpt-the-battle-for-ai-powered-education-dominance-" title="Direct link to chegg-vs-chatgpt-the-battle-for-ai-powered-education-dominance-">​</a></h2><p>Chegg, an online education company, and its encounter with the disruptive force of generative AI, particularly OpenAI's ChatGPT. Chegg's executives had previously considered the potential of AI to replace human instructors and reduce costs but underestimated the rapid pace at which consumers embraced tools like ChatGPT.</p><p>Initially, Chegg didn't view ChatGPT as a threat to its paid services. However, when OpenAI released GPT-4, students began opting for ChatGPT instead of Chegg's paid offerings, leading to a significant loss in subscriber growth and a decline in the company's market value.</p><p>Despite their efforts, Chegg's future remains uncertain, and the company's executives are focused on navigating the challenges posed by generative AI to stay relevant in the education industry.</p><div class="footnotes"><hr><ol><li id="fn-1-d9f119"><a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-palm-2-ai-large-language-model/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-palm-2-ai-large-language-model/</a><a href="#fnref-1-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-2-d9f119"><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/05/22/1073471/metas-new-ai-models-can-recognize-and-produce-speech-for-more-than-1000-languages/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/05/22/1073471/metas-new-ai-models-can-recognize-and-produce-speech-for-more-than-1000-languages/</a><a href="#fnref-2-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-3-d9f119"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/may/25/artificial-intelligence-antibiotic-deadly-superbug-hospital" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/may/25/artificial-intelligence-antibiotic-deadly-superbug-hospital</a><a href="#fnref-3-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-4-d9f119"><a href="https://news.adobe.com/news/news-details/2023/Adobe-Unveils-Future-of-Creative-Cloud-with-Generative-AI-as-a-Creative-Co-Pilot-in-Photoshop-default.aspx/default.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://news.adobe.com/news/news-details/2023/Adobe-Unveils-Future-of-Creative-Cloud-with-Generative-AI-as-a-Creative-Co-Pilot-in-Photoshop-default.aspx/default.aspx</a><a href="#fnref-4-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-5-d9f119"><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/05/24/1073395/ai-in-cybersecurity-yesterdays-promise-todays-reality/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/05/24/1073395/ai-in-cybersecurity-yesterdays-promise-todays-reality/</a><a href="#fnref-5-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-6-d9f119"><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/05/23/spotify-may-use-ai-to-make-host-read-podcast-ads-that-sound-like-real-people/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://techcrunch.com/2023/05/23/spotify-may-use-ai-to-make-host-read-podcast-ads-that-sound-like-real-people/</a><a href="#fnref-6-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-7-d9f119"><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/chegg-embraced-ai-chatgpt-ate-its-lunch-anyway/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.wired.com/story/chegg-embraced-ai-chatgpt-ate-its-lunch-anyway/</a><a href="#fnref-7-d9f119" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li></ol></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>mind-benders</category>
            <category>ai</category>
            <category>tmai</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (Part - 1)]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-artificial-intelligence</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-artificial-intelligence</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Taking you on a journey of Artificial Intelligence, its humble beginnings to the present day.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Unlock the mystery of AI with this epic multi-part series, taking you on a journey from its humble beginnings to the present day. Join us as we explore different aspects of Artificial Intelligence in this entire series.</p></blockquote><p>Artificial Intelligence (AI) is an exciting and rapidly growing field that has the potential to transform our world in countless ways. From self-driving cars to virtual personal assistants, AI has already made its way into many aspects of our daily lives, and its applications continue to expand.</p><p>Artificial Intelligence is composed of two words <strong>Artificial</strong> and <strong>Intelligence</strong>, where Artificial defines <em>“man-made,”</em> and intelligence defines <em>“thinking power”</em>, hence AI means <em>“a man-made thinking power.”</em></p><blockquote><p>Artificial Intelligence is a branch of computer science by which we can create intelligent machines which can behave like a human, think like humans, and able to make decisions.</p></blockquote><p>But what exactly is AI, and how did it come to be? In this article, we’ll take a brief look at the history of AI and its evolution over time.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="early-concepts-of-ai">Early Concepts of AI<a href="#early-concepts-of-ai" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Early Concepts of AI" title="Direct link to Early Concepts of AI">​</a></h3><p>The idea of machines that could mimic human intelligence dates back centuries, with early examples including the ancient Greek myths of Talos, a giant bronze statue that could move and act on its own, and Pygmalion’s statue, which was brought to life by the goddess Aphrodite.</p><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Figure 1 - Talos" src="/assets/images/Talos-99635ba9cc9b8ad3ee96ee48dd6dea3a.webp" width="300" height="207" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Figure 1 — Talos by <a href="https://technicacuriosa.com/author/amayor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Adrienne Mayor</strong></a></em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>In the modern era, the concept of AI began to take shape in the mid-20th century. In 1950, computer scientist Alan Turing proposed the “Turing Test,” which is still used today to measure a machine’s ability to exhibit intelligent behavior equivalent to, or indistinguishable from, that of a human.</p><p>Early AI research focused on rule-based systems, in which machines were programmed to follow a set of explicit rules to solve problems. While these systems were effective for some tasks, they were limited by their inflexibility and inability to learn from experience.</p><p>AI has many sub-categories like Machine Learning and Deep Learning. People usually tend to use these terms interchangeably. Let’s look at these terms in brief -</p><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Figure 2 - Sub-categories of AI" src="/assets/images/sub-categories-of-AI-2947772424544dabf498e73f16f88e61.webp" width="628" height="628" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Figure 2 — By the <a href="https://medium.com/@nidhiworah02" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Author</a> — Types of Artificial Intelligence</em></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-rise-of-machine-learning">The Rise of Machine Learning<a href="#the-rise-of-machine-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Rise of Machine Learning" title="Direct link to The Rise of Machine Learning">​</a></h2><p>In the 1980s, a new approach to AI emerged: Machine Learning. This approach involved designing algorithms that could learn from data, identify patterns, and make predictions based on that data.</p><p>Machine learning algorithms were initially used for simple tasks such as recognizing handwritten characters, but their applications quickly expanded to more complex problems, including speech recognition, image recognition, and natural language processing.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="deep-learning-and-neural-networks">Deep Learning and Neural Networks<a href="#deep-learning-and-neural-networks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Deep Learning and Neural Networks" title="Direct link to Deep Learning and Neural Networks">​</a></h2><p>In the 2010s, a subfield of machine learning known as deep learning began to emerge, fueled by advances in computing power and data storage. Deep learning algorithms are modeled after the structure and function of the human brain, using artificial neural networks to simulate the behavior of neurons and synapses.       </p><p>Deep learning has enabled breakthroughs in areas such as image and speech recognition and has led to the development of autonomous vehicles and other advanced technologies.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-future-of-ai">The Future of AI<a href="#the-future-of-ai" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Future of AI" title="Direct link to The Future of AI">​</a></h2><p>As AI continues to advance, its potential applications are virtually limitless. From personalized healthcare to smart homes and cities, AI has the power to revolutionize nearly every aspect of our lives.</p><p>As Uncle Ben says, “With great power comes great responsibility.” AI systems become more sophisticated, it’s important to ensure that they are designed and deployed ethically and responsibly, with consideration for issues such as bias, privacy, and security.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="types-of-artificial-intelligence">Types of Artificial Intelligence<a href="#types-of-artificial-intelligence" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of Artificial Intelligence" title="Direct link to Types of Artificial Intelligence">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Figure 3 - Types of AI" src="/assets/images/types-of-AI-68125fbe3195e3a65b8ea998b1185023.webp" width="786" height="608" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Figure 3 — By the <a href="https://medium.com/@nidhiworah02" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Author</a> — Types of Artificial Intelligence</em></td></tr></tbody></table><br><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="artificial-intelligence--type-1-based-on-capabilities">Artificial Intelligence — Type 1: Based on Capabilities<a href="#artificial-intelligence--type-1-based-on-capabilities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence — Type 1: Based on Capabilities" title="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence — Type 1: Based on Capabilities">​</a></h3><p><strong>Narrow AI</strong></p><ul><li>Narrow AI is a type of AI that is able to perform a dedicated task with intelligence.</li><li>Narrow AI cannot perform beyond its field or limitations, as it is only trained for one specific task. Hence it is also termed weak AI. Narrow AI can fail in unpredictable ways if it goes beyond its limits.</li><li>Some Examples of Narrow AI are playing chess, purchasing suggestions on e-commerce sites, self-driving cars, speech recognition, and image recognition.     </li></ul><p><strong>General AI</strong></p><ul><li>General AI is a type of intelligence that could perform any intellectual task with efficiency like a human.</li><li>The idea behind the general AI is to make such a system that could be smarter and think like a human on its own.</li><li>It is currently a hypothetical concept, and we don’t yet have any real-world examples of this type of AI.</li></ul><p><strong>Super AI</strong></p><ul><li>Super AI is a level of Intelligence of Systems at which machines could surpass human intelligence, and can perform any task better than humans with cognitive properties. It is an outcome of general AI.</li><li>Super AI is still a hypothetical concept of Artificial Intelligence. The development of such systems in real is still world changing task.</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="artificial-intelligence--type-2-based-on-functionality">Artificial Intelligence — Type 2: Based on Functionality<a href="#artificial-intelligence--type-2-based-on-functionality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence — Type 2: Based on Functionality" title="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence — Type 2: Based on Functionality">​</a></h3><p><strong>Reactive Machines</strong></p><ul><li>Purely reactive machines are the most basic types of Artificial Intelligence.</li><li>Such AI systems do not store memories or past experiences for future actions.</li><li>These machines only focus on current scenarios and react to them as per the possible best action.</li><li>Examples: IBM’s Deep Blue system, Google’s AlphaGo</li></ul><p><strong>Limited Memory</strong></p><ul><li>Limited memory machines can store past experiences or some data for a short period of time.</li><li>These machines can use stored data for a limited time period only.</li><li>Self-driving cars are one of the best examples of Limited Memory systems. These cars can store the recent speed of nearby cars, the distance of other cars,
the speed limit, and other information to navigate the road.</li></ul><p><strong>Theory Of Mind</strong></p><ul><li>Theory of Mind AI should understand human emotions, people, and beliefs, and be able to interact socially like humans.</li><li>This type of AI machine is still not developed, but researchers are making lots of efforts and improvements for developing such AI machines.</li></ul><p><strong>Self-Awareness</strong></p><ul><li>Self-awareness AI is the future of Artificial Intelligence. These machines will be super intelligent and will have their own consciousness, sentiments, and
self-awareness.</li><li>These machines will be smarter than the human mind.</li><li>Self-Awareness AI does not exist in reality still and it is a hypothetical concept.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>Artificial intelligence has come a long way since the early days of rule-based systems, and its evolution shows no signs of slowing down. With ongoing research
and development, the potential applications of AI are vast and ever-expanding.</p><p>If you enjoy reading stories on similar topics then do <a href="https://medium.com/@nidhiworah02/subscribe" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">follow</a> the account. Let me know your thoughts below</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
            <category>Machine Learning</category>
            <category>Data</category>
            <category>Data Science</category>
            <category>Automation</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This Month in AI - April 2023]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-april-2023</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/tmai-april-2023</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Latest News & Breakthroughs in the Month of April 2023 in AI/ML/DS.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="A robotic hand touching a speck of light" src="/assets/images/tmai-apr23-poster-74e12b955d98b100ed101d726ae7229e.png" width="1587" height="2245" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="unlock-the-power-of-bingai-experience-the-future-today-">Unlock the Power of BingAI: Experience the Future, Today! <sup id="fnref-1-c1178c"><a href="#fn-1-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup><a href="#unlock-the-power-of-bingai-experience-the-future-today-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to unlock-the-power-of-bingai-experience-the-future-today-" title="Direct link to unlock-the-power-of-bingai-experience-the-future-today-">​</a></h2><p>Microsoft has made Bing AI accessible to the public, eliminating the waitlist requirement. Users can now try out the AI bot by signing in to Bing using their Microsoft account on the Edge browser. The latest update introduces several exciting features powered by OpenAI's technologies. </p><p>Also, Bing AI now supports rich "visual answers," displaying graphs, charts, and formatted content. The Bing Image Creator has been upgraded to support over 100 languages, enabling the generation of AI images based on text prompts and visual examples. Additionally, users can export and share chats, benefit from improved summarization capabilities for long documents, and enjoy actions within Edge for quicker access to relevant content. Microsoft is also developing third-party plug-ins to expand functionality within Bing Chat.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="linkedins-intelligent-assistance-craft-the-perfect-job-application-">LinkedIn's Intelligent Assistance: Craft the Perfect Job Application <sup id="fnref-2-c1178c"><a href="#fn-2-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup><a href="#linkedins-intelligent-assistance-craft-the-perfect-job-application-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to linkedins-intelligent-assistance-craft-the-perfect-job-application-" title="Direct link to linkedins-intelligent-assistance-craft-the-perfect-job-application-">​</a></h2><p>LinkedIn is reportedly testing an AI-powered feature that provides personalized writing suggestions for job seekers, aiming to help them create tailored job applications. The feature generates short cover letter-like messages using information from the user's profile, the hiring manager's profile, the job description, and the targeted company. While the AI-generated drafts serve as a starting point, LinkedIn emphasizes the importance of customization and encourages users to review and edit the suggestions to reflect their own voice and style. </p><p>This development builds upon LinkedIn's existing AI writing tool for profile creation. The adoption of AI in job application drafting reflects the growing interest in artificial intelligence, with its potential to enhance user experiences and improve outcomes in various industries, including recruitment and career development.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="yolo-nas-revolutionizing-object-detection-with-unprecedented-precision-">YOLO-NAS: Revolutionizing Object Detection with Unprecedented Precision <sup id="fnref-3-c1178c"><a href="#fn-3-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup><a href="#yolo-nas-revolutionizing-object-detection-with-unprecedented-precision-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to yolo-nas-revolutionizing-object-detection-with-unprecedented-precision-" title="Direct link to yolo-nas-revolutionizing-object-detection-with-unprecedented-precision-">​</a></h2><p>Deci AI, a deep learning firm, has unveiled YOLO-NAS, its latest deep learning model designed for real-time object detection with remarkable performance. Built on Deci's Neural Architecture Search Technology, AutoNAC™, YOLO-NAS outperforms other models like YOLOv6, YOLOv7, and YOLOv8, including the recently launched YOLOv8. AutoNAC democratizes Neural Architecture Search, enabling organizations to create customized, fast, accurate, and efficient deep learning models quickly. </p><p>YOLO-NAS delivers superior throughput, achieving 50% more throughput and 1 mAP higher accuracy compared to other YOLO models. It is pre-trained on popular datasets, making it suitable for various real-world applications. The open-source model is available with pre-trained weights for non-commercial research use on Deci's PyTorch-based computer vision training library called SuperGradients.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introducing-starcoder-free-code-generating-assistant-">Introducing StarCoder: Free Code-Generating Assistant <sup id="fnref-4-c1178c"><a href="#fn-4-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">4</a></sup><a href="#introducing-starcoder-free-code-generating-assistant-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to introducing-starcoder-free-code-generating-assistant-" title="Direct link to introducing-starcoder-free-code-generating-assistant-">​</a></h2><p>Hugging Face and ServiceNow Research have jointly released StarCoder, a free code-generating model that offers an alternative to existing AI systems like GitHub's Copilot. StarCoder, part of the BigCode project, was trained on over 80 programming languages and integrates with Microsoft's Visual Studio Code editor. Unlike other commercial models, StarCoder is royalty-free and available for use by anyone, including corporations. </p><p>The project aims to develop state-of-the-art AI systems for code generation in an open and responsible manner. StarCoder's release comes amidst debates around the use of public source code and licensing agreements for training AI models, with efforts made to address privacy concerns and adhere to ethical best practices.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="geoffrey-hinton-ais-threat-could-be-more-urgent-than-climate-change-">Geoffrey Hinton: AI's Threat Could Be 'More Urgent' Than Climate Change <sup id="fnref-5-c1178c"><a href="#fn-5-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">5</a></sup><a href="#geoffrey-hinton-ais-threat-could-be-more-urgent-than-climate-change-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to geoffrey-hinton-ais-threat-could-be-more-urgent-than-climate-change-" title="Direct link to geoffrey-hinton-ais-threat-could-be-more-urgent-than-climate-change-">​</a></h2><p>In a recent interview, renowned AI pioneer Geoffrey Hinton expressed his concerns that the threat posed by artificial intelligence (AI) to humanity could be even more urgent than climate change. Hinton, often referred to as one of the "godfathers of AI," believes that the risks associated with AI technology are significant and warrant immediate attention. Having recently left Alphabet, Hinton intends to speak out about these risks without any constraints from his former employer. As the debate around AI's impact on society continues to unfold, Hinton's remarks highlight the need for careful consideration and proactive measures to ensure the responsible and ethical development and deployment of AI technologies.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="accelerating-the-quest-for-new-metals-ml-offers-a-promising-solution-">Accelerating the Quest for New Metals: ML Offers a Promising Solution <sup id="fnref-6-c1178c"><a href="#fn-6-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">6</a></sup><a href="#accelerating-the-quest-for-new-metals-ml-offers-a-promising-solution-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to accelerating-the-quest-for-new-metals-ml-offers-a-promising-solution-" title="Direct link to accelerating-the-quest-for-new-metals-ml-offers-a-promising-solution-">​</a></h2><p>Machine learning could help develop new types of metals with useful properties, such as resistance to extreme temperatures and rust, according to new research. This could be useful in a range of sectors—for example, metals that perform well at lower temperatures could improve spacecraft, while metals that resist corrosion could be used for boats and submarines.
Usually they start off with one well-known element, like iron, which is cheap and malleable, and add one or two others to see the effect on the original material. It’s a laborious process of trial and error that inevitably yields more duds than useful results.
Researchers from the Max Planck Institute managed to identify 17 promising new metals using this method.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="revolutionizing-ml-researchers-unveil-a-more-agile-approach-">Revolutionizing ML: Researchers Unveil a More Agile Approach <sup id="fnref-7-c1178c"><a href="#fn-7-c1178c" class="footnote-ref">7</a></sup><a href="#revolutionizing-ml-researchers-unveil-a-more-agile-approach-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to revolutionizing-ml-researchers-unveil-a-more-agile-approach-" title="Direct link to revolutionizing-ml-researchers-unveil-a-more-agile-approach-">​</a></h2><p>Artificial intelligence researchers have celebrated a string of successes with neural networks, computer programs that roughly mimic how our brains are organized. In 2020, two researchers at the MIT led a team that introduced a new kind of neural network based on real-life intelligence — but not our own. After a breakthrough last year, the novel networks may now be versatile enough to supplant their traditional counterparts for certain applications.</p><p>Liquid neural networks offer an elegant and compact alternative , said Ken Goldberg, a roboticist at the University of California, Berkeley. These networks can run faster and more accurately than other so-called continuous-time neural networks, which model systems that vary over time</p><div class="footnotes"><hr><ol><li id="fn-1-c1178c"><a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2023/02/22/the-new-bing-preview-experience-arrives-on-bing-and-edge-mobile-apps-introducing-bing-now-in-skype/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2023/02/22/the-new-bing-preview-experience-arrives-on-bing-and-edge-mobile-apps-introducing-bing-now-in-skype/</a><a href="#fnref-1-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-2-c1178c"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-ai-can-help-you-land-your-dream-job-step-by-step-hemachandran/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-ai-can-help-you-land-your-dream-job-step-by-step-hemachandran/</a><a href="#fnref-2-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-3-c1178c"><a href="https://deci.ai/blog/yolo-nas-object-detection-foundation-model/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://deci.ai/blog/yolo-nas-object-detection-foundation-model/</a><a href="#fnref-3-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-4-c1178c"><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/05/04/hugging-face-and-servicenow-release-a-free-code-generating-model/amp/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://techcrunch.com/2023/05/04/hugging-face-and-servicenow-release-a-free-code-generating-model/amp/</a><a href="#fnref-4-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-5-c1178c"><a href="https://theconversation.com/ai-pioneer-geoffrey-hinton-says-ai-is-a-new-form-of-intelligence-unlike-our-own-have-we-been-getting-it-wrong-this-whole-time-204911" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://theconversation.com/ai-pioneer-geoffrey-hinton-says-ai-is-a-new-form-of-intelligence-unlike-our-own-have-we-been-getting-it-wrong-this-whole-time-204911</a><a href="#fnref-5-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-6-c1178c"><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/10/25/1062104/machine-learning-new-metals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/10/25/1062104/machine-learning-new-metals</a><a href="#fnref-6-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li><li id="fn-7-c1178c"><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/researchers-discover-a-more-flexible-approach-to-machine-learning-20230207" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.quantamagazine.org/researchers-discover-a-more-flexible-approach-to-machine-learning-20230207</a><a href="#fnref-7-c1178c" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li></ol></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>mind-benders</category>
            <category>ai</category>
            <category>tmai</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rotaract Club of TCET]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/rotaract-club-of-tcet</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/rotaract-club-of-tcet</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[About Rotaract Club of TCET]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Are you one of those engineers who are just engrossed in academics and is looking to do something more than that in your college days? Rotaract Club of TCET is one of the perfect choices to go for. I f you are searching to participate in something interesting where you can develop yourself and volunteer as well, you are at the correct place. To know more continue reading this blog.</p></blockquote><h1>‘Boldly Going: Rotaract Club of TCET '</h1><p><img loading="lazy" alt="RCTCET" src="/assets/images/RCTCET-88117ce8c71f5cea6c3adc4891094210.png" width="2000" height="1600" class="img_ev3q"></p><blockquote><p><em>"The purpose of life is to live it, to taste experience to the utmost, to reach out eagerly and without fear for newer and richer experience."</em> </p><p><em>-Eleanor Roosevelt</em></p></blockquote><p>Whether you're a musician, artist, athlete, writer, or simply someone who loves trying new things, Rotaract Club of TCET offers a welcoming and inclusive community where you can connect with like-minded individuals and pursue your passions. From workshops and classes to group outings and events, RCTCET provides a variety of opportunities for personal growth, skill development, and social interaction. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="types-of-projects--events-conducted-in-rctcet">Types of Projects &amp; Events conducted in RCTCET<a href="#types-of-projects--events-conducted-in-rctcet" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of Projects &amp; Events conducted in RCTCET" title="Direct link to Types of Projects &amp; Events conducted in RCTCET">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="1-volunteering">1. Volunteering<a href="#1-volunteering" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Volunteering" title="Direct link to 1. Volunteering">​</a></h3><p>Volunteering in community service related projects or events can help you gain practical experience while also contributing to your community.By volunteering, individuals can gain a deeper understanding of community needs and become more empathetic towards others.Community service volunteering activities are a valuable way to give back to the community and make a positive impact on society. They provide individuals with opportunities to engage in meaningful work, develop new skills, build relationships, and gain a sense of personal fulfillment.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="few-volunteering-events">Few volunteering events:<a href="#few-volunteering-events" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Few volunteering events:" title="Direct link to Few volunteering events:">​</a></h4><ul><li>TechWorld</li>This is a flagship (activities which happens throughout the year) activity where we teach the underprivileged about electronic circuits and create awareness amongst them to pursue Engineering as a career, to mentor younger students for their bright future.</ul><ul><li>Emergency</li>The main aim of conduction of this event is to make our budding Engineers well aware how to perform CPR and give first aid to someone in need.</ul><ul><li>Beach Cleanup</li>Such events are conducted by keeping the welfare of the community and balance of ecosystem in mind. This could be possible only with the contribution of people who are genuinely interested in volunteering. Afterall,"If you concentrate on small, manageable steps you can cross unimaginable distances."</ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2-space-to-socialize">2. Space to Socialize<a href="#2-space-to-socialize" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Space to Socialize" title="Direct link to 2. Space to Socialize">​</a></h3><p>Joining clubs and organizations is a great way to meet people who share your interests such as sports, music, etc. It is an amazing platform to meet new people and develop bonding. Remember, socializing in college can be challenging at first, but it's important to step out of your comfort zone and take advantage of opportunities to meet new people. Be yourself, have fun, and enjoy the college experience! We have fun Club Service (Avenue) Events which promotes students to know each other irrespective of their branches and to have fun together releasing the academic exhaustion aside.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="examples-of-such-socializing-events">Examples of such socializing events:<a href="#examples-of-such-socializing-events" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Examples of such socializing events:" title="Direct link to Examples of such socializing events:">​</a></h4><div><ul><li>Sunday Funday</li><li>Treasure Hunt</li><li>Movie Night</li><li>Badminton Tournament</li><li>Kick it!(Football Tournament)</li></ul></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="3-space-to-express-creativity">3. Space to express creativity<a href="#3-space-to-express-creativity" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Space to express creativity" title="Direct link to 3. Space to express creativity">​</a></h3><p>Rotaract Club of TCET provides a cavity to students where they can express their artistic or literary talents. Members can explore different genres of writing, such as poetry, fiction, creative nonfiction, and screenwriting. They can also participate in writing prompts and exercises, which can help them generate new ideas and experiment with different writing styles. Students can showcase their work through public readings and publications. For our members possessing artistic talent, be it in the form of paper or digitalized form of art they can contribute by means of Digital Communication. They can learn, grow and experiment at the same time. For individuals who love to capture beautiful moments they can come forward and give their photography skills a boost. People who are good at branding they are welcomed as well where they can fully utilise their Social Media Marketing skills.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="4-development-of-overall-personality">4. Development of Overall Personality<a href="#4-development-of-overall-personality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Development of Overall Personality" title="Direct link to 4. Development of Overall Personality">​</a></h3><p>Participating in co-curricular activities can be extremely beneficial for your personal and professional development. Our club can help you learn about the business side of engineering and develop skills such as project management, leadership, and communication. We often organize events such as pitch competitions, guest speakers, and mentorship programs.</p><p>We conduct events wherein students learn how to develop Interpersonal Skills, they can participate in group activities, attend workshops and seminars on communication and collaboration, practice active listening, and seek feedback from peers and instructors. Building strong interpersonal skills takes time and effort, but it is a valuable investment for future success.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="5-last-but-not-the-least-it-is-a-platform-where-you-can-create-amazing-memories">5. Last but not the least, it is a platform where you can create amazing memories!<a href="#5-last-but-not-the-least-it-is-a-platform-where-you-can-create-amazing-memories" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Last but not the least, it is a platform where you can create amazing memories!" title="Direct link to 5. Last but not the least, it is a platform where you can create amazing memories!">​</a></h3><p><img loading="lazy" alt="RCevent" src="/assets/images/RCevent-29e8422d8d09cec17bb89368b957eb22.jpg" width="1500" height="1000" class="img_ev3q"></p><blockquote><p><em>"Education is not just about academics. It's about building character, improving one's personality, and becoming a better human being."</em> </p><p><em>- Sudha Murty</em></p></blockquote><p>Joining RCTCET can create can create amazing memories for students. It is a complete new experience where you can participate in different kinds of fun events. Opportunities to travel together, whether it's a weekend camping trip or a day trip to a nearby city the experience is wonderful. Volunteering for a social cause develops a sense of responsibility in young individuals. Competing with your peers gives you confidence to do better than before. Sharing same interests with someone new helps you create memorable experiences. College days are something a student cherishes for life and it is grateful to have a platform as such.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="to-know-more-about-us">To know more about us:<a href="#to-know-more-about-us" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to To know more about us:" title="Direct link to To know more about us:">​</a></h2><p>Visit our <a href="https://www.rctcet.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Official Website</strong></a>
And do follow us <a href="https://www.instagram.com/rc_tcet/?hl=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>@rc_tcet</strong></a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>Remember, co-curricular activities are meant to complement your academic studies. Make sure to balance your time and commitments so that you can excel both academically and personally. Don't be afraid to step out of your comfort zone and try something new. Joining a club as Rotaract Club of TCET can be a rewarding and fun experience that creates memories that last a lifetime. Moreover, social clubs can help promote social cohesion and strengthen community ties. They can offer a sense of belonging and provide a platform for individuals to come together and work towards common goals. In short, Rotaract Club of TCET can be a fun and enriching way to connect with others and build community. By joining this club, individuals can expand their horizons, create new friendships, and contribute to a more vibrant and inclusive society.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>cultural</category>
            <category>social</category>
            <category>community</category>
            <category>editorial</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dive into Web Design 🖌️ | Learn the Mental Model for converting Designs into Code]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/dive-into-web-design</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/dive-into-web-design</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Understanding Design and Converting it into Code]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Web designing (the HTML &amp; CSS part, not the Figma Part) can be a real pain if we don’t understand the design system/rules/procedure it uses. Even after watching HTML and CSS tutorials, we can still struggle to design anything in web. But, after having a decent <strong>understanding of divisions</strong> into <strong>rows</strong> and <strong>columns</strong> and learning about <strong>display properties and positioning</strong> in detail, you we can have some confidence to <strong>turn any Figma design to HTML and CSS</strong>. This is not a tutorial on HTML &amp; CSS but a comprehensive usage of them. By reading this blog, I hope you can get the confidence and create the <strong>Mental Model of Web Design in your Brain</strong> ✨</p><p>This Blog also serves as a very precise summary of long web design bootcamp I took with <a href="https://twitter.com/genosis_x" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">**GenosisX Tech Community</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLMSrWOO6hvLqdfCkNaQ1GhslVzvKygjU0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>watch here</em></a>**</p><blockquote><p>TL;DR: Create proper rows and columns for each block of design, put them into proper semantic tags or <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> tags. Use display flex or grid on them. Then style them properly with the fonts, colors, paddings, margins, borders, backgrounds. Position them properly with position property of CSS. Use responsive features of flex and grid. Done!</p></blockquote><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="prerequisite">Prerequisite<a href="#prerequisite" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Prerequisite" title="Direct link to Prerequisite">​</a></h2><ul><li>Basic knowledge of HTML and CSS would help, but not necessary.</li><li>That’s It!</li></ul><h1>Guide to Divisions</h1><p>Making proper divisions of design into rows and columns will help you style them better and will make it 100x easier to make them responsive. Let’s get into it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="visualize-design">Visualize Design<a href="#visualize-design" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Visualize Design" title="Direct link to Visualize Design">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ik.imagekit.io/okaydokeymypath/blogs/deep-dive-into-web-design/visualize_divisions_1.gif" alt="Visualize Design #1" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Visualize Design #1</p><ul><li>First think of the separate sections, in this case, there are two, a Header and a Hero section.</li><li>For every block of divisions, first think of sections as in one row or one column, then multiple columns or rows respectively.</li><li>Divisions<ul><li>Here, the whole page is one column which has two rows, Navbar and Hero.</li><li>Then we clearly see, hero is divided into two columns, so hero itself is one row which has two different distinct columns.</li><li>You can try to dig further deep into each div visually.</li></ul></li></ul><p>So based upon the divisions, we can conclude the following code.</p><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, whole page --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Row, Header --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Row, Hero section --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, Main Text Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Column, Main Image Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="lets-dig-deep">Lets dig deep<a href="#lets-dig-deep" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Lets dig deep" title="Direct link to Lets dig deep">​</a></h3><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ik.imagekit.io/okaydokeymypath/blogs/deep-dive-into-web-design/visualize_divisions_2.gif" alt="Visualize Design #2" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Visualize Design #2</p><ul><li>Divisions - Header - a row<ul><li>Img - Logo - First column</li><li>Navbar - Second column</li><li>Button - Third column</li></ul></li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, whole page --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Row, Header --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">bunch of </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> Tags</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Sign up</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Row, Hero section --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, Main Text Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Column, Main Image Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">  </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><blockquote><p>Use semantic tags wherever possible, they hold some meaning and are very important for SEO, read this article to learn more about them. <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/guides/semantic-html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.pluralsight.com/guides/semantic-html</a></p></blockquote><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ik.imagekit.io/okaydokeymypath/blogs/deep-dive-into-web-design/visualize_divisions_3.gif" alt="Visualize Design #3" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Visualize Design #3</p><ul><li>Divisions - Main - a row<ul><li>First Column of Hero Section<ul><li>H1 - Main text - First row</li><li>p - Description text - Second row</li><li>span - Third Row having two buttons<ul><li>Button - First Column</li><li>Button - Second Column</li></ul></li></ul></li><li>Second Column of Hero Section<ul><li>img - First Column</li></ul></li></ul></li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, whole page --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Row, Header --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">bunch of </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> Tags</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Sign up</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Row, Hero section --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, Main Text Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">h1</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Main text...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">h1</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">p</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Description text...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">p</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">span</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Get Started</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Order Now</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">span</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Column, Main Image Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">  </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h1>Guide to Style them</h1><p>Pat yourself if you reached till here, and understood everything above! Lets go ahead.</p><p>For the next part, I’ll use tailwindcss because it’s easier to explain with. If you know CSS, you basically know tailwindcss. Read this article for a quick introduction, I hope you come back here after reading this. <a href="https://tailwindcss.com/docs/utility-first" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tailwindcss.com/docs/utility-first</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="step-by-step-linear-process-to-design-anything">Step-by-Step Linear Process to Design Anything!<a href="#step-by-step-linear-process-to-design-anything" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step-by-Step Linear Process to Design Anything!" title="Direct link to Step-by-Step Linear Process to Design Anything!">​</a></h2><p>Remember, this is not a hard and fast rule to follow exactly as is. You can add you own flavours to this. Skip steps which are not required. I made this using my personal experience so add modify it if I missed anything. </p><ol><li>Write HTML, using the divisions approach</li><li>Set background color</li><li>Set display - flex (if any child tags)</li><li>Set width - compulsory</li><li>Set height - optional</li><li>set overflow properties</li><li>Set font → size, weight, line height, letter spacing, </li><li>Set text colors → paddings → borders → margins <ol><li>Colors - normal, hover, active any states</li><li>Borders - width/thickness , color, radius, style</li></ol></li><li>Set position (if want to move the element from its position)<ol><li>relative - move it from its current position</li><li>absolute - move it from its <strong>first relative parent</strong> start point (top-0, left-0 of relative parent)</li><li>fixed - move it from windows start point (top-0, left-0 of whole window)</li></ol></li><li>Set z-index - define stack, which element should be above which</li><li>Anything else that suits your design</li></ol><p>This is a linear process, which means you first style the first tag then the second tag then the third tag then the next tag then the next tag and so on!</p><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First style this #1 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- then this #2 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Then this #3 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Then this #4 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">..</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Then this #5 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">..</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Then this #6 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">..</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Then this #7 --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- and so on till the last tag --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Sign up</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">h1</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Main text...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">h1</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">p</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Description text...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">p</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">span</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Get Started</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Order Now</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">span</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="here-comes-the-css">Here comes the CSS<a href="#here-comes-the-css" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Here comes the CSS" title="Direct link to Here comes the CSS">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ik.imagekit.io/okaydokeymypath/blogs/deep-dive-into-web-design/web_design.png" alt="Web Design Bootcamp Design" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Web Design Bootcamp Design</p><p>Take a quick look, and we will start with the linear process</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="body---main-page">Body - main page<a href="#body---main-page" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Body - main page" title="Direct link to Body - main page">​</a></h3><p>We can see that the </p><ul><li>background color is different</li><li>width is full screen</li><li>padding left and right i.e x-axis</li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">bg-[#f3f3f3] w-[100vw] px-16 </span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, whole page --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Row, Header --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">            ...</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="header">Header<a href="#header" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Header" title="Direct link to Header">​</a></h3><p>Here,</p><ul><li>We see, everything is in one row, so set display as flex</li><li>width is full available space so 100%</li><li>img - logo<ul><li>width of some pixels</li></ul></li><li>navbar<ul><li>width of fit content (automatic)</li><li>font weight is medium i.e 500</li><li>Color is gray for all but black for current one</li></ul></li><li>button<ul><li>background is orange</li><li>text is bold</li><li>longer padding in x-axis, shorted padding in y-axis</li><li>border radius full rounded</li></ul></li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">body</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">bg-[#f3f3f3] w-[100vw] px-20 </span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, whole page --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">flex w-full</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Row, Header --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">w-20</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">flex w-fit text-[#828282] font-medium</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">id</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">current</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">text-black</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Home</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">       </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- if id="current" then class="text-black" add this login using javascript  --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">How it works</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">a</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      ...</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">nav</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">bg-[#FF6F1E] w-fit text-white px-4 py-2 rounded-full</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">Sign up</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second column --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">header</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">     ...</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><p>We won’t do the whole design, but this will give you enough idea on how we go about designing and how to follow the linear process which may seem overwhelming but is really easy to follow.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="responsiveness-how-easy-is-it">Responsiveness, how easy is it?<a href="#responsiveness-how-easy-is-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Responsiveness, how easy is it?" title="Direct link to Responsiveness, how easy is it?">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="desktop-first-design-approach">Desktop First Design Approach<a href="#desktop-first-design-approach" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Desktop First Design Approach" title="Direct link to Desktop First Design Approach">​</a></h3><ul><li>First we design the desktop version of our web app</li><li>Then slowly add rules to make it responsive for tablets then mobile</li><li>Desktop → Tablet → Mobile</li><li>This is not recommended</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="mobile-first-design-approach">Mobile First Design Approach<a href="#mobile-first-design-approach" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Mobile First Design Approach" title="Direct link to Mobile First Design Approach">​</a></h3><ul><li>First we design the mobile version of our web app</li><li>Then slowly add rules to make it responsive for tablets then desktop</li><li>Mobile → Tablet → Desktop</li><li>This is most recommended and used by tailwindcss by default</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="no-media-query-methods">No media query methods<a href="#no-media-query-methods" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to No media query methods" title="Direct link to No media query methods">​</a></h3><ul><li>Set max-widths and min-widths</li><li>Use display flex with flex-wrap, flex-grow, flex-shrink, flex-basis</li><li>Use display grid with grid-template-columns, repeat - autofit, minmax</li><li>You can much deeper with maths to avoid media queries but I feel that much is unnecessary.</li><li>Using some media queries to avoid extreme complexity is always a good idea</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="a-good-example-of-minimum-media-queries">A good example of minimum media queries<a href="#a-good-example-of-minimum-media-queries" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A good example of minimum media queries" title="Direct link to A good example of minimum media queries">​</a></h3><p><strong><strong>****</strong></strong>The prefix <strong>lg:</strong> is how we use media queries in tailwindcss, refer this* <a href="https://tailwindcss.com/docs/responsive-design" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tailwindcss.com/docs/responsive-design</a></p><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">flex flex-wrap text-lg lg:text-xl m-5 lg:m-10</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Row, Hero section --&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">max-w-lg</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- First Column, Main Text Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      ...</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">max-w-lg</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Column, Main Image Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">      ...</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">main</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="get-creative-with-positioning">Get Creative with Positioning<a href="#get-creative-with-positioning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Get Creative with Positioning" title="Direct link to Get Creative with Positioning">​</a></h2><p>When we want to move some elements from their original position to something else, we use position property.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="css-positions">CSS Positions<a href="#css-positions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to CSS Positions" title="Direct link to CSS Positions">​</a></h3><ul><li>Static<ul><li>Default value</li><li>Original position, cannot change it.</li></ul></li><li>Relative<ul><li>Set explicitly</li><li>Can change position from original using properties - top, left, bottom, right</li><li>Moves towards the specified direction from its current position.</li></ul></li><li>Absolute<ul><li>Set explicitly</li><li>Can change position from original using properties - top, left, bottom, right</li><li>Move towards the specified direction from the <strong>first relative parents</strong> start coordinates.</li></ul></li><li>Fixed<ul><li>Set explicitly</li><li>Can change position from original using properties - top, left, bottom, right</li><li>Move towards the specified direction from the coordinates of <strong>window (browser tab)</strong> itself</li><li>Does not move on scroll, stays fixed.</li></ul></li></ul><blockquote><p>This article by MDN teaches all positionings perfectly.
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/position" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/position</a></p></blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="an-example-of-positioning">An example of positioning<a href="#an-example-of-positioning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to An example of positioning" title="Direct link to An example of positioning">​</a></h3><p>Lets look at the image which has blocks of elements floating above it.</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ik.imagekit.io/okaydokeymypath/blogs/deep-dive-into-web-design/pizza_design.png" alt="Pizza Design" class="img_ev3q"></p><ul><li>So the concept is we wrap the image in one div</li><li>This div will be set to position: relative</li><li>This div will contain image tag and other elements of those floating blocks</li><li>Don’t change image tag position</li><li>Change position: absolute of all floating elements</li><li>Then set them to their places via top, left, right, bottom</li></ul><div class="language-html codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-html codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">relative</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token comment" style="color:#999988;font-style:italic">&lt;!-- Second Column, Main Image Section--&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">img</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">w-24 h-40</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">  </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">src</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">/..</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">/&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">absolute top-[30%] right-[-10%]</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">absolute top-[50%] left-[-10%]</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">class</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">absolute bottom-[-15%] right-[12%]</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain">...</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">div</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">section</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h1>Conclusion</h1><ul><li>Make proper divisions while writing the whole HTML. Visualize and then create rows and columns.</li><li>Write whole HTML of one section then style the whole section using the step by step linear process.</li><li>Position properly and most of it depends on the parents element position property, so make sure you set those correct.</li><li>Learn flex, grid and positions of CSS very thoroughly.</li><li>Learn tailwindcss because it will make your life easier, trust me on this.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Web Design</category>
            <category>HTML</category>
            <category>CSS</category>
            <category>Mental Model</category>
            <category>Resonsiveness</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[6 Reasons Why React JS is the Future of Web Development!!]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-react-js</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-react-js</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Why React JS is the Future of Web Development]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><b>As</b> technology continues to evolve, web development has become an increasingly important field, and front-end frameworks such as ReactJS have emerged as crucial tools for building dynamic, user-friendly websites. Whether you are just starting out with web development or are looking to enhance your existing skills, I hope that you will find valuable insights and tips within these pages. So sit back, grab a cup of coffee, and join me on our journey through the exciting world of ReactJS!</blockquote><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="“Design is not just what it looks like and feels like. Design is how it works.” — Steve Jobs" src="/assets/images/reactjs-c0e8ca45355fd1d3795bac16f3a9d5ba.png" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>“Design is not just what it looks like and feels like. Design is how it works.” — Steve Jobs</em></td></tr></tbody></table><br><h1>What is React JS?</h1><p>React JS is nothing but a java script library that helps the developers in creating reusable UI components there by increasing the efficiency of code. When making dynamic websites React JS is proven to be more effective than Vanilla JS, and hence it has become a popular choice for building fast and scalable single-page applications. In simple terms, ReactJS helps make web development more efficient, organized, and dynamic.</p><h1>Characteristic Features of React JS that makes it more versatile and Popular</h1><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Features of ReactJS" src="/assets/images/characteristics-125cdd46a3b8383771d4052fb7c4840b.png" width="1246" height="848" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Features of ReactJS</em></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="1-virtual-dom">1. Virtual DOM<a href="#1-virtual-dom" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Virtual DOM" title="Direct link to 1. Virtual DOM">​</a></h2><p>In traditional web development, when changes are made to a web page, the entire page needs to be re-rendered, which can be slow and time-consuming. The Virtual DOM solves this issue by creating a virtual representation of the web page in memory so when changes are made, ReactJS updates the virtual DOM instead of the actual page, which is much faster. Then, ReactJS compares the virtual DOM to the actual page and updates only the parts that have changed, rather than the entire page. This makes the updates and rendering process much faster and more efficient, improving the overall user experience of the web application.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2-reusable-components">2. Reusable Components<a href="#2-reusable-components" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Reusable Components" title="Direct link to 2. Reusable Components">​</a></h2><p>ReactJS uses a component-based architecture, which means that the user interface is built using reusable components. Each component is a self-contained unit that handles a specific task or displays a specific piece of information, we can say that each components are independent. This makes the code more organized and easier to maintain, as well as reducing the amount of redundant code.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="3-community">3. Community<a href="#3-community" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Community" title="Direct link to 3. Community">​</a></h2><p>React has a vast and supportive community of developers who are constantly contributing new features and tools. React is open-source, meaning that anyone can contribute to the development of the library by fixing bugs, adding new features, or improving existing ones.</p><blockquote><p><a href="https://github.com/facebook/react" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Link to contribute to the React Library</em></a></p></blockquote><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="4-jsx">4. JSX<a href="#4-jsx" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. JSX" title="Direct link to 4. JSX">​</a></h2><p>JSX stands for JavaScript XML. It is a syntax extension for JavaScript used by ReactJS that allows developers to write HTML-like code within their JavaScript. This makes it easier for users to write and understand the code, as it closely resembles the structure of HTML. This helps to improve the overall development experience by making the code more intuitive and easier to read.</p><p>For example, instead of writing the following code in pure JavaScript to render a simple button:</p><div class="language-js codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-js codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token maybe-class-name">React</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:#d73a49">createElement</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">(</span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"button"</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">className</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"myButton"</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"Click Me!"</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><p>The same code can be written in JSX as:</p><div class="language-jsx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-jsx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f"> </span><span class="token tag attr-name" style="color:#00a4db">className</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation attr-equals" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag attr-value" style="color:#e3116c">myButton</span><span class="token tag attr-value punctuation" style="color:#393A34">"</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token plain-text">Click Me!</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&lt;/</span><span class="token tag" style="color:#00009f">button</span><span class="token tag punctuation" style="color:#393A34">&gt;</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="5-server-side-rendering">5. Server-side Rendering<a href="#5-server-side-rendering" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Server-side Rendering" title="Direct link to 5. Server-side Rendering">​</a></h2><p>Server-side rendering (SSR) is the process of rendering a web page on the server before sending it to the browser. In the case of React, this means that the React components can be rendered on the server, allowing the browser to receive a fully rendered HTML page, instead of having to wait for JavaScript to execute and render the page on the client side again and again.</p><p>This results in faster initial load times, as the browser doesn’t have to wait for the JavaScript to execute and render the page. Additionally, server-side rendering can improve Search Engine Optimization (SEO), as search engines can better index and understand the content of the page.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="6-compatibility">6. Compatibility<a href="#6-compatibility" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Compatibility" title="Direct link to 6. Compatibility">​</a></h2><p>React’s simplicity and straightforward design makes it easy for developers to learn and adopt and it works seamlessly with other libraries and frameworks, such as Redux, allowing developers to create complex and scalable web applications.</p><h1>Comaprison with other Frontend Frameworks</h1><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Popular Web Frameworks" src="/assets/images/chart1-d4f0fed815d934614a0a42789400d9a7.png" width="1042" height="810" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Comparison with other frameworks as per the recent survey</em></td></tr></tbody></table><blockquote><p>Source: Stack Overflow Developer Survey 2021</p></blockquote><p>From the above survey it can be clearly seen that React JS was named as one on the most commonly used web Framework.</p><p>React’s virtual DOM provides fast updates and rendering compared to traditional DOM manipulation. Angular and Vue also have optimized updates, but they may not be as fast as React’s virtual DOM.</p><p>Also, React is known for its simplicity and minimalistic approach, making it relatively easy to learn and get started with. Angular, on the other hand, has a steeper learning curve due to its more complex architecture. Vue falls somewhere in between, offering a more accessible learning experience as compared to Angular.</p><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info alert alert--info admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>You can see more detailed insights of React JS on their <a href="https://reactjs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Official Website</strong></a></p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>In conclusion, React is the future of web development, offering a robust set of features and tools that make it easy to build high-performing, scalable, and maintainable web applications. Its simplicity, performance, and compatibility with other technologies make it an excellent choice for modern web development.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>ReactJs</category>
            <category>JSX</category>
            <category>Virtaul DOM</category>
            <category>Frontend</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloud Computing: Revolutionizing the Way We Store and Access Data]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-cloud-computing</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/intro-to-cloud-computing</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Cloud Computing: Revolutionizing the Way We Store and Access Data]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This Blog talks about the emerging trends in Cloud computing, and also gives a gist about the term Cloud Computing and its impact in leveraging businesses and individuals. The cloud has the ability to streamline and improve a variety of processes. From understanding the meaning of cloud computing model to discussing various characteristics, this blog will be your one-stop-shop for all things cloud computing. So, fasten your seatbelts and let's dive into the exciting world of the cloud together!!</p></blockquote><br><h1>What is Cloud Computing ?</h1><p>Cloud computing is a way of using current technology where we can access and use internet-based services and storage to manage, process, and store data and information, instead of having to have it all on your own personal device or computer. </p><p>We can think of it like having access to a giant computer in the sky that we can use to do our work, store our files, and run our applications, without having to worry about the technical details or maintenance of the underlying hardware and software. This makes it easier and more convenient for us to access our data and resources from anywhere in the world, as long as we have an internet connection.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="lets-take-a-look-at-some-intriguing-features-of-cloud-computing">Let's take a look at some intriguing features of Cloud Computing!!<a href="#lets-take-a-look-at-some-intriguing-features-of-cloud-computing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Let's take a look at some intriguing features of Cloud Computing!!" title="Direct link to Let's take a look at some intriguing features of Cloud Computing!!">​</a></h2><br><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>🛠️ On-Demand Self-Service</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div><p>With cloud computing, we can provision computing services, like server time and network storage, automatically. No communication with the service provider will be necessary. Customers of cloud services can view their cloud services, track their usage, and provision and de-provision services by logging into their cloud accounts through a web self-service portal.</p></div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>💻 Broad Network Access</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div><p>Broad network connectivity is another crucial aspect of cloud computing. Through a network and on portable devices like smartphones, tablets, laptops, and desktop PCs, we can access cloud services. A private cloud employs a local area network, whereas a public cloud uses the internet. Broad network access and cloud computing both rely heavily on latency and bandwidth since they have an impact on service quality.</p></div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>📝 Resource Pooling</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div><p>With resource pooling, multiple customers can share physical resources using a multi-tenant model. Based on demand, this model distributes and redistributes real and virtual resources. Customers can share the same applications or infrastructure with multi-tenancy while still retaining their privacy and security. Customers may be able to designate the location of their resources at a higher level of abstraction, such as a country, state, or data centre, even though they won't know the precise location of their resources. Customers can pool a variety of resources, including memory, computing power, and bandwidth.</p></div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>🔗 Rapid Elasticity</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div><p>Cloud services can be elastically provisioned and released, sometimes automatically, so customers can scale quickly based on demand, thus making it highly scalable. The capabilities available for provisioning are practically unlimited. Customers can use these features whenever they want and in whatever amount. Customers can scale cloud capacity, cost, and usage without incurring additional contracts or charges. We won't need to acquire computer hardware thanks to quick elasticity. </p></div></div></div></details><details class="details_lb9f alert alert--info details_b_Ee" data-collapsed="true"><summary><b>⚙️ Measured Service</b></summary><div><div class="collapsibleContent_i85q"><div><p>A metering capability in cloud systems optimises resource utilisation at an abstraction level appropriate for the type of service. For storage, processing, bandwidth, and users, for instance, we can utilise a metered service. A pay-for-what-you-use model is used to base payments on the customer's actual consumption. Consumers and service providers benefit from a transparent experience that is created by monitoring, managing, and reporting resource use.</p></div></div></div></details><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="lets-have-a-look-at-some-of-the-most-used-cloud-storage-services">Lets have a look at some of the most used Cloud Storage Services<a href="#lets-have-a-look-at-some-of-the-most-used-cloud-storage-services" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Lets have a look at some of the most used Cloud Storage Services" title="Direct link to Lets have a look at some of the most used Cloud Storage Services">​</a></h2><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Most Used Cloud Storage Services" src="/assets/images/most-used-cloud-storage-services-56caeaf20934163f276dc7a4eb3619b0.png" width="1233" height="849" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Most used Cloud Storage Services</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Google Drive is by far the most popular cloud storage service in the world, with an use rate of <strong>94.44 percent</strong>. The finest cloud storage for collaboration, Dropbox, is in second position with a still-impressive <strong>66.2 percent</strong>, followed by <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-in/microsoft-365/onedrive/online-cloud-storage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>OneDrive</strong></a> <strong>(39.35 percent)</strong> and <a href="https://www.icloud.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>iCloud</strong></a> <strong>(38.89 percent)</strong>. Additionally popular cloud storage providers include <a href="https://mega.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>MEGA</strong></a> <strong>(5.09 percent)</strong>, <a href="https://www.box.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Box</strong></a> <strong>(4.17 percent)</strong>, and <a href="https://www.pcloud.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>pCloud</strong></a> <strong>(1.39%)</strong>, all of which made our list of the top cloud storage services.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="statistics-on-cloud-service-providers">Statistics on Cloud Service Providers<a href="#statistics-on-cloud-service-providers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Statistics on Cloud Service Providers" title="Direct link to Statistics on Cloud Service Providers">​</a></h2><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Stats on Cloud Service Providers" src="/assets/images/cloud-provider-market-share-trend-250cce2abe0dc96085a0300e9c4a4480.jpg" width="756" height="490" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Stats on Cloud Service Providers</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>AWS still holds over a third of the cloud services market:</p><ul><li>In Q2 2022, <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>AWS</strong></a> commanded <strong>34%</strong> of the cloud market, a <strong>1%</strong> increase year-over-year. <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Azure</strong></a> is second with <strong>21%</strong> of the market, followed by <a href="https://cloud.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Google Cloud</strong></a> <strong>(10%)</strong>, <a href="https://in.alibabacloud.com/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Alibaba</strong></a> <strong>(5%)</strong>, and <a href="https://www.ibm.com/cloud" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>IBM</strong></a> <strong>(4%)</strong>.</li><li>Amazon's revenue from AWS grew from <strong>5.62</strong> in 2014 to <strong>13.24%</strong> in 2021.</li><li>The survey also showed the cloud market continues to grow <strong>34%</strong> year-over-year.</li></ul><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-tip alert alert--success admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 12 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.5 0C3.48 0 1 2.19 1 5c0 .92.55 2.25 1 3 1.34 2.25 1.78 2.78 2 4v1h5v-1c.22-1.22.66-1.75 2-4 .45-.75 1-2.08 1-3 0-2.81-2.48-5-5.5-5zm3.64 7.48c-.25.44-.47.8-.67 1.11-.86 1.41-1.25 2.06-1.45 3.23-.02.05-.02.11-.02.17H5c0-.06 0-.13-.02-.17-.2-1.17-.59-1.83-1.45-3.23-.2-.31-.42-.67-.67-1.11C2.44 6.78 2 5.65 2 5c0-2.2 2.02-4 4.5-4 1.22 0 2.36.42 3.22 1.19C10.55 2.94 11 3.94 11 5c0 .66-.44 1.78-.86 2.48zM4 14h5c-.23 1.14-1.3 2-2.5 2s-2.27-.86-2.5-2z"></path></svg></span>FunFact</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>It took Netflix seven years to migrate to AWS</p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="some-drawbacks-to-have-a-look-upon">Some drawbacks to have a look upon<a href="#some-drawbacks-to-have-a-look-upon" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Some drawbacks to have a look upon" title="Direct link to Some drawbacks to have a look upon">​</a></h2><br><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Drawbacks of Cloud Computing" src="/assets/images/drawback-be09b82a7aa33d85e129fefeda9c3125.jpg" width="740" height="459" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Drawbacks of Cloud Computing</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>According to cybersecurity experts, the most pressing cloud security challenges are misconfiguration of the cloud infrastructure <strong>(68 percent)</strong>; unauthorized access <strong>(58 percent)</strong>; insecure API <strong>(52 percent)</strong>; accounts, services or traffic hijacking <strong>(50 percent)</strong> and external data sharing <strong>(43 percent)</strong>.</p><div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info alert alert--info admonition_LlT9"><div class="admonitionHeading_tbUL"><span class="admonitionIcon_kALy"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_S0QG"><p>If you are interested in finding out more about cloud security, we have an <a href="https://www.cloudwards.net/cloud-security/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">excellent article detailing cloud security measures</a> for cloud storage services.</p></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><ul><li>In conclusion, cloud computing has become an increasingly popular and indispensable tool for businesses and organizations of all sizes. With its ability to provide on-demand access to a wide range of computing resources, including storage, computing power, and applications, it has transformed the way organizations operate and has unlocked new opportunities for innovation and growth.</li><li>The cloud offers many benefits, including cost savings, scalability, increased efficiency, and improved security. As more and more businesses adopt cloud computing, it is likely that this trend will continue to grow, driving further innovation and enabling organizations to do more with less.</li><li>However, while the benefits of cloud computing are clear, there are also challenges that must be addressed, such as ensuring data security, managing vendor lock-in, and ensuring reliable performance.</li><li>Despite these challenges, the future of cloud computing looks bright, with advancements in areas such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, and the Internet of Things set to further drive its growth and revolutionize the way businesses operate.</li></ul><p>In short, cloud computing is here to stay, and its impact on the business world will only continue to grow in the years to come.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>cloud computing</category>
            <category>data</category>
            <category>source</category>
            <category>software</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Breaking The Ice - Open Source]]></title>
            <link>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/breaking-the-ice-open-source</link>
            <guid>https://opensource.tcetmumbai.in/blog/breaking-the-ice-open-source</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Breaking The Ice - Open Source]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Project management is a wild way to make sure things are progressing as they should. There is a project management technique for everything. Well, almost everything. I haven't found a project managing concept to overcome my feelings of procrastination. Someone might create it one day.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-really-is-open-source">What really <em>is</em> Open Source?<a href="#what-really-is-open-source" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-really-is-open-source" title="Direct link to what-really-is-open-source">​</a></h2><p>If you're the engineering type of person that tackles humanity's problems and urgent needs by bringing together an entire community and building a "project" with them, you'll want to know about <strong>Open source</strong>. Open source refers to a philosophy of software development that emphasizes collaboration, transparency, and community-driven innovation. </p><p>Here it is again in bigger letters, for impact:</p><blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="open-source-refers-to-a-philosophy-of-software-development-that-emphasizes-collaboration-transparency-and-community-driven-innovation">Open source refers to a philosophy of software development that emphasizes collaboration, transparency, and community-driven innovation.<a href="#open-source-refers-to-a-philosophy-of-software-development-that-emphasizes-collaboration-transparency-and-community-driven-innovation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Open source refers to a philosophy of software development that emphasizes collaboration, transparency, and community-driven innovation." title="Direct link to Open source refers to a philosophy of software development that emphasizes collaboration, transparency, and community-driven innovation.">​</a></h3></blockquote><p>And now you know what open source is. <em>In theory, this blog post could be done!</em></p><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="beyond-the-marketing-standpoint">Beyond the marketing standpoint<a href="#beyond-the-marketing-standpoint" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Beyond the marketing standpoint" title="Direct link to Beyond the marketing standpoint">​</a></h3><p>Technology is a concept which is ever-changing in how it is defined, its magnitude and how we as engineers develop it. In the world of technology we always find "buzz words" which reflect the recent advancements which are so efficient that they are slowly brought within the industry as a standard way of working on projects, as a team.</p><p>One such "buzz word" in the area of software development and project management is open source. Open source is a way of working on a software typically developed in a public, collaborative manner, with the source code made freely available to anyone who wants to use, modify, or distribute it. The term "open source" was coined in 1998 by a group of people in the software industry who wanted to create a new model of software development that was more collaborative and community-driven.</p><p>Open source software is often developed and maintained by a community of volunteers and contributors, who work together to improve the software and fix bugs. Consider your <strong>homework</strong>: a dry document which contains things here and there which you know is very incomplete. If you have a good enough personality <em>(which I don't)</em>, you send this document to all your classmates who start doing bits of your homework.</p><p><em>The result?</em> A fine specimen of a document which the entire class can show to your teachers for great marks! What you just did here was open sourcing your homework and let your student community work on it to create a more appealing document which is now complete.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="but-open-source-doesnt-stop-there">But open source doesn't stop there<a href="#but-open-source-doesnt-stop-there" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to But open source doesn't stop there" title="Direct link to But open source doesn't stop there">​</a></h3><p>Imagine your homework to be your project, your classmates to be your community. This community observes your project and suggests various improvements within it. Be it suggesting simple changes of changing the fonts or re-working the already existing complex APIs and queries.</p><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Example of suggestions" src="/assets/images/meme-3f02107546e1509819bbf9cf8f9832fc.jpg" width="677" height="698" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>A simple conversation between a contributor and a project developer</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Another way to look at open source can be building the big <strong>Lego City</strong> together, block by block. Everyone can add their own pieces to what has been constructed so far and everyone can see how the city is made. In this way, everyone can make the city better and use it how they want.</p><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Software Engineers" src="/assets/images/budding-062eaa508fb2d9a041277969ac4ae620.jpg" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Budding software engineers collaborating to build their project</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Open source is a great way to bring like-minded developers together. Everybody around you, be a fresher student or an industry experienced individual, has had to encounter with open source technologies without even realizing it. From something we daily use like <strong>Android</strong> to <strong>Linux</strong>: the operating system used by many corporates and tech giants, there's no saying what the next big thing will be.</p><table><thead><tr><th align="center"><img loading="lazy" alt="Open Source" src="/assets/images/open-8953a127882dbb7f6a3c79eceaa7660e.jpg" width="659" height="499" class="img_ev3q"></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><em>Python, Dart, React, MongoDB, even this text box is open source</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>That's about the gist of what I wished to express regarding open source. Surely that's not everything but I do look forward to go in-depth into this topic and talk about various different things which excite me! Do look forward to upcoming blogposts and reach me out for any constructive criticism, if any, for the future blogposts.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>free</category>
            <category>open</category>
            <category>source</category>
            <category>software</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>